<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A taste of the spirit of God, and of this vvorld, as they have appeared in opposition heretofore, so now latest of all at New-Windsor. Occasioned through the violence, and reproach of evil men, against the temple and tabernacle of God, and them that dwel therein. Presented in a narrative to the honourable committee, for the propagating the Gospel. / By Robert Bacon, preacher by the allowance of God, and the nation, now these five years there.</title>
            <author>Bacon, Robert, M.A.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77079</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B371</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E669_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207030</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866105</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866105</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118367</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77079)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118367)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 103:E669[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A taste of the spirit of God, and of this vvorld, as they have appeared in opposition heretofore, so now latest of all at New-Windsor. Occasioned through the violence, and reproach of evil men, against the temple and tabernacle of God, and them that dwel therein. Presented in a narrative to the honourable committee, for the propagating the Gospel. / By Robert Bacon, preacher by the allowance of God, and the nation, now these five years there.</title>
                  <author>Bacon, Robert, M.A.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at his shop at the sign of the black spread Eagle, at the West end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Respecting the treatment of the author there." -- Thomason catalogue.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 6".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Clergy --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Missionaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118367:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TASTE OF The Spirit of God, AND OF THIS WORLD, AS THEY Have appeared in oppoſition here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, ſo now lateſt of all at <hi>New-Windſor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Occaſioned through the violence, and reproach of evil men, againſt the <hi>Temple</hi> and <hi>Tabernacle</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and them that <hi>dwel therein.</hi> Preſented in a Narrative to the Honourable Committee, for the propagating the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>By ROBERT BACON, Preacher by the allowance of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Nation,</hi> now theſe five years there.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 50.</hi>
                  </bibl> I kept <hi>ſilence,</hi> and thou <hi>thoughteſt</hi> I was ſuch a <hi>one</hi> as thy <hi>ſelf;</hi> but I will <hi>reprove thee,</hi> and ſet [all] in <hi>order</hi> before <hi>thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Aſſiduum <hi>cum mundo</hi> bellum <hi>gerant</hi> neceſſe eſt, <hi>qui</hi> propheticam fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem fidelitér <hi>&amp;</hi> ſinceré <hi>obire volunt.</hi> 
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Calv. in Eſa. in Epiſt. ad Edw. 6. Ang. Reg.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſign of the black ſpread Eagle, at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118367:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118367:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee for the <hi>propagating</hi> the <hi>Goſpel, Robert Bacon</hi> of <hi>new Windſor,</hi> wiſheth <hi>illumination</hi> in the <hi>things,</hi> in the <hi>which</hi> they are <hi>concern'd.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is meet that to <hi>you</hi> above all <hi>others</hi> in the Land, next to thoſe that have <hi>entruſted</hi> you, I ſhould preſent this following diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and <hi>teſtimony;</hi> by which may <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear</hi> in part, what the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is, of which men talk ſo <hi>much,</hi> and <hi>know ſo little</hi> in theſe times: as likewiſe what <hi>ado</hi> and <hi>trouble</hi> ariſeth in the World from men of <hi>corrupt minds,</hi> concerning it, to whom it muſt needs be (it <hi>could not be the Goſpel elſe</hi>) ſo great a <hi>Rock</hi> of <hi>offence,</hi> that they would (whether <hi>Jew</hi> or
<note n="*" place="margin">For as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaith, the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>both</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth in <hi>oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to the <hi>Goſpel</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven till now.</note> 
               <hi>Gentile,</hi> that believe not) that any other thing <hi>ſhould be,</hi> then it, <hi>allowed,</hi> and found among men; for as much as it doth <hi>detect,</hi> not only <hi>other,</hi> but the moſt <hi>hidden</hi> and <hi>ſecret evils,</hi> are either in the <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>life</hi> of men; ſo that they <hi>hate</hi> it, no otherwiſe then doth the <hi>Malefactor</hi> the Judge, when he comes not only to diſcover, but to <hi>give judgment</hi> on him; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt <hi>honourable men,</hi> you and the <hi>power</hi> entruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you, will find it no eaſie, yea a ſcarce poſſible thing, to ſecure <hi>it</hi> from the <hi>reproach</hi> and <hi>violence</hi> of <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> men, as hath been evident from the <hi>beginning,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb facs="tcp:118367:3"/>
               <hi>till now:</hi> I ſhall only crave leave humbly thus much to <hi>beg</hi> of you, in this your ſo great <hi>undertake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> that in the things of <hi>this nature, as well,</hi> and more then <hi>others,</hi> you rather <hi>in your hearts</hi> conſult <hi>with God,</hi> then <hi>man,</hi> leaſt there be of men introduced <hi>another Goſpel, then that which is indeed the power of God unto ſalvation;</hi> wherefore unleſs you have been in ſome meaſure <hi>on the Mount with God,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Jeſus</hi> was, I know not how <hi>poſsible</hi> you <hi>will,</hi> or <hi>can</hi> be able to <hi>determine of things</hi> of ſo <hi>divine</hi> and <hi>hidden nature;</hi> if yet indeed you have not hereunto <hi>attained,</hi> without all <hi>peradventure,</hi> you will <hi>find,</hi> and the <hi>State</hi> entruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you, that your <hi>attaining</hi> this, but to a <hi>willing mind,</hi> that <hi>no violence be uſed of one Neighbor,</hi> or <hi>man, againſt another,</hi> as <hi>touching theſe things,</hi> is the <hi>best,</hi> and <hi>moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent attainment</hi> hath yet been in the <hi>Land,</hi> ſince it was <hi>firſt called Chriſtian;</hi> for you ſhall <hi>find</hi> by this <hi>diſcourſe,</hi> what <hi>violence</hi> would ſoon be uſed againſt the <hi>truth, as it is in Jeſus,</hi> unleſs either it be <hi>repeld</hi> by <hi>force</hi> of <hi>humane power,</hi> or more <hi>Divinely overcome,</hi> by the <hi>patient love and meekneſs of them,</hi> with whom is the <hi>Lamb Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> as their <hi>head</hi> and <hi>guide,</hi> to whom I beſeech <hi>God</hi> you may be <hi>willing</hi> (with <hi>others</hi>) to <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit</hi> yourſelves, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118367:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader, if he underſtand.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> 
               <hi>Would</hi> advertize <hi>thee, however I make mention of the</hi> names <hi>of many, and thoſe</hi> ſome <hi>of them of the</hi> greateſt note, <hi>and</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minency <hi>among men in the</hi> Land; <hi>yet I have</hi> done it, <hi>not in</hi> prejudice <hi>to any, or to</hi> defame, <hi>even the</hi> meaneſt, <hi>to which this diſcourſe doth</hi> relate; <hi>for there is</hi> nothing <hi>in the World</hi> I mind more; <hi>then a</hi> healing of all <hi>the</hi> evil <hi>and</hi> hearts (<hi>if it were</hi> poſſible <hi>in this</hi> Land) <hi>which I am</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitly endeared <hi>unto, to</hi> ſerve <hi>in the</hi> Lord, <hi>and in</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>this</hi> Town, <hi>and</hi> People <hi>of</hi> Windſor, <hi>to whom I am much</hi> endebted, <hi>for the</hi> love ſake of God unto me, <hi>that</hi> even <hi>to</hi> them <hi>I am</hi> ready, notwithſtanding <hi>their ſtrong endeavour to</hi> withſtand <hi>me, to</hi> continue <hi>to preach the</hi> Goſpel freely; only <hi>this I have</hi> done, <hi>I moſt</hi> free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>acknowledge, to no other</hi> intent, <hi>then</hi> if <hi>by</hi> any means, <hi>at least</hi> ſome <hi>of them,</hi> might awake out of ſleep, ariſe up from among the dead, <hi>in</hi> treſpaſſes and ſins, that they might have life given them, even that for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more: <hi>and that they might</hi> ſo do, <hi>I have</hi> begged of God, <hi>that they might hear</hi> his voyce, if not <hi>in my</hi> preaching, yet <hi>in my</hi> ſuffering; <hi>and if in neither of</hi> them, <hi>then in this</hi> my writing, <hi>which for their</hi> ſake, <hi>I
<pb facs="tcp:118367:4"/>have thus</hi> produced, <hi>rather then</hi> mine own; <hi>I could have been</hi> exceedingly <hi>well</hi> content, <hi>to have</hi> continued <hi>in the</hi> ſtill enjoyment, <hi>of my</hi> moſt dear Lord, <hi>in my</hi> retirement <hi>under the</hi> reproach <hi>and</hi> ſcorn <hi>of</hi> men; for there is a ſecret delight given me of God, which the World is not a ware of, <hi>and</hi> which I am ſure, through the grace of God I enjoy, that I am as well pleaſed with a Crown of thorns, as with one of Gold, yea, and a thouſand fold more: <hi>yet it being the</hi> will of God, <hi>to bear the</hi> affronts <hi>don</hi> him in me <hi>no</hi> longer, <hi>as</hi> hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; <hi>for he hath not</hi> hid himſelf <hi>(I may ſay truly)</hi> here <hi>from</hi> ſhame <hi>and</hi> ſpitting; <hi>I am</hi> content <hi>at his</hi> bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>to go</hi> down <hi>as</hi> Moſes <hi>did, to reaſon the</hi> matter <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout</hi> Iſrael <hi>with</hi> Pharaoh (<hi>the</hi> head <hi>and</hi> King <hi>of the</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil people <hi>and</hi> things in this place) <hi>a</hi> ſervice <hi>of</hi> my ſelf, <hi>I would not,</hi> for a World undertake; <hi>be it known there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> unto thee, <hi>who ever</hi> thou art, <hi>that</hi> underſtands, <hi>that the time of the</hi> true Churches freedom, <hi>or</hi> deliverance <hi>is</hi> come, <hi>yea the</hi> ſet time <hi>of</hi> it <hi>is</hi> come: Wherefore <hi>thus ſaith the</hi> Lord, my ſword (<hi>his</hi> ſore, great, <hi>and ſtrong</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">His Word of Might, or his mighty Word.</note> Sword) <hi>ſhal be</hi> bathed in heaven, behold it ſhal come down upon Idumea, <hi>and</hi> upon the people <hi>of my</hi> curſe <hi>to</hi> judgment: <hi>Wherefore (alſo)</hi> cry out <hi>and</hi> ſhout <hi>thou</hi> inhabitreſſe <hi>of</hi> Zion; <hi>for</hi> great <hi>is the</hi> holy one <hi>of</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael [Thy King Jehovah] <hi>thy truſt and hope, in</hi> the midſt of thee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:118367:4"/>
            <head>The Heads of this whole Diſcourſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Sect. 1. A <hi>Brief of the Authours ſufferings from his youth, with the Teſtimony of the love of God to him therein.</hi> pag. 1.</item>
               <item>Sect. 2. <hi>A very brief Relation, of whom, and in what manner the Miniſtry hath appeared and been manifeſt, and manag'd in this place, ſince the Authours firſt coming.</hi> p. 2, 3</item>
               <item>Sect. 3. <hi>A Letter of enquiry, directed to the Miniſters, after a while combin'd in a Lecture at</hi> Windſor, <hi>together with the event thereof, in concluſion.</hi> p. 4, 5</item>
               <item>Sect. 4. <hi>A diſcovery of the ſuppoſed means, and certain manner of the awakening of the rude and heady people of this place.</hi> p. 5.</item>
               <item>Sect. 5. <hi>The Diſcourſe had at a certain meeting or veſtry of the people, aſſembled for the having of a Vicar.</hi> p. 6.</item>
               <item>Sect. 6. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon what account, and why withſtood in this of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour,</hi> viz. <hi>becauſe they went about to make them a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, to lead them back again into</hi> Aegipt. p. 6. 7</item>
               <item>Sect. 7. <hi>A ſecond letter, with the occaſion of it, directed as a caſe of Conſcience, to be determined of the Preachers, and of their ſilence as to it.</hi> p. 8, 9</item>
               <item>Sect. 8. <hi>A Relation of the Diſcourſe had with the new deſired Vicar, together with a taſte of his Doctrine, and manner of thruſting himſelf upon the people.</hi> p. 9, 10, 11.</item>
               <item>Sect. 9. <hi>How this matter was repreſented to the Lord</hi> Whitlock, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Holland <hi>the Burgeſs of this place, by a letter to the latter, with the event thereof.</hi> p. 12, 13, 14</item>
               <item>Sect. 10. <hi>A digreſſion touching an exception taken at the Authours Sermon, by the Preachers here, with the account and ground why.</hi> p. 14, 15</item>
               <item>Sect. 11. <hi>An account of the Authours Journey for a viſiting of the people that know and fear the Lord in ſome part of the</hi> Weſt, <hi>and how it doth relate to this diſcourſe.</hi> p. 15.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:118367:5"/>
               <item>Sect. 12. <hi>The offence taken at his unexpected return, and for what cauſe likened of ſome to</hi> Moſes <hi>his ſudden coming down from the Mount, with the manner of the rude people, their behaviour towards the Authour, with the event of his being among them, as to the Sacrament, and their taking the name of God in vain, with their leader, in that thing.</hi> p. 16, 17, 18, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Sect. 13. <hi>Of the endeavour of the people, by all means to defame the Authour, eſpecially by a note procur'd by one Mr.</hi> Baker, <hi>from, as 'tis ſaid, the Aſſembly of Divines; concerning which, ſomething is ſpoke as to vindication, with a Letter of Mr.</hi> Bachilers <hi>to Mr.</hi> Holland, <hi>upon that occaſion,</hi> p. 21, 22</item>
               <item>Sect. 14. <hi>Of the great abuſe of all humane, as well as of the divine Authority of God (his Word) at</hi> Windſor, <hi>with a Letter to the Mayor from the Burgeſs of this place; and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors Obſervation, Teſtimony, reproach, and Reaſon of his crying out under all, now at laſt.</hi> p. 23, 24, 25, &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The firſt Poſtſcript.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Containing, A Letter, giving light to the fore-paſt Diſcourſe, to the Councel of State.</hi> p. 29.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Letter to the Lord General</hi> Cromwel. p. 30, 31</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Letter to the Governor</hi> C. Whitchcot. p. 32, 33.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Letter in the name of the Town to Mr.</hi> Holland. p. 34, 35</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Authors two Proteſtations,</hi> p. 36, 37.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The ſecond Poſtſcript.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Touching a report given out by one Mr</hi> Wood, <hi>now of</hi> Eaton, <hi>againſt the Author, with a true Relation of the manner and ground of it.</hi> p. 38, 39, 40, &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Pag. 17. lin. laſt, read <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Pag. 28. l. 35. for <hi>una</hi> r. <hi>vera.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pag. 37. l. 8. r. <hi>as I and ſome others.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118367:5"/>
            <head>A taste of the Spirit of God, and of this World, as they have appeared in oppoſition heretofore, ſo now latest of all at New Windſor.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving been now theſe many years converſant, through the Grace of God, in giving teſtimony in the things that concern the life that is <hi>for ever,</hi> as in my youth at <hi>Oxford,</hi> afterwards at <hi>Bristol, Wiltſhire, Glocester, London,</hi> and now theſe laſt five years at <hi>Windſor;</hi> in all which as I have taſted, felt, and found oppoſition, wrath, fury, yea Phrenſie, from ſome of all ſorts and degrees of men, the chief and Ringleaders being in all places ſome of thoſe commonly, though abuſively enough, cal'd the <hi>Clergie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Gildas</hi> his epiſtle. the latter end.</note> for ſo it is, as it hath been ſaid, <hi>Clerus Angliae ſtupor mundi;</hi> for as for others in compariſon of theſe, it may be ſaid, alas, <hi>what evil have they done?</hi> ſo I have had in all theſe places and conflicts, a ſeal of Gods love, and powerfull <hi>quickening preſence,</hi> to enliven me in death (for I have been in <hi>deaths oft</hi>) and to enlighten and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port me, in the midſt of thoſe many clouds and darkneſſes, have ſo often come upon me; ſo that as the Almighty hath been, and doth remain, and ever will the ſame to me, ſo have I through his grace and moſt effectuall love, remained (being kept in <hi>his Son</hi>) entire and true to him, though through many difficulties, dangers, temptations, tryals, weakneſſes, reproaches, contradictions, as are and hath been <hi>the faithful</hi> in all ages more or leſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118367:6"/>
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <p>I have judged it in my heart before the <hi>Lord,</hi> meet in this junc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of time, for the furtherance of the cauſe and Kingdome of God, now much talkt of, and in ſome degree <hi>come in our own Land,</hi> to make publique this laſt encounter I have met with now laſt of all, from the combined and fully (it ſeems) reſolved and rude people of <hi>New Windſor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as leading to that I will mention the matter briefly, as it hath related to me there, from my firſt coming to this place (to which I was importun'd by the then, and as yet Governour of this Caſtle, as likewiſe by the Mayor and Gentlemen of the Town and others, in the which Mr. <hi>Bachiler</hi> now Fellow of <hi>Eaton</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge was principally inſtrumentall) there was then living one Mr. <hi>Cleaver,</hi> who according to the account of the Nation had the Name, Title, and Place of <hi>Vicar,</hi> during his life almoſt conſtantly I taught every morning on the Sabboth day in the Caſtle, a while in the ſtead of Mr <hi>Bachiler,</hi> but his Chaplainſhip failing, I conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in ſo doing for the continuance of the ſolemn meeting, upon mine own offer, and the Governours acceptance and deſire, almoſt till the death of Mr. <hi>Cleaver,</hi> and till a little after the coming of Mr. <hi>Simons.</hi> About this time there was offence taken, and no little ado made, as touching my <hi>Doctrine, Purpoſe, Faith,</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Life.</hi> the particulars whereof I lift not now to make pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, but ſhall if God will hereafter; but the event was, that as to Miniſtry and preaching I was to be no more in the Caſtle, for it was determined, none was better, then that which was judged worſe, even worſe then nothing, <hi>the price at which the Son of God himſelf was, and at this day is, of the world rated.</hi> Upon this there being a vacancie in the Town in the morning, through the death of the forenamed Vicar, I was to my ſeeming ſomewhat gladly as wel as oportunly deſired, and did offer my ſelf to be with them, then, aſwell as in the afternoon; in this ſervice I continued a while, till it was bruited that I had no Warrant from the Nation in this thing; my former order expiring, together with Mr <hi>Cleaver</hi> it being onely to continue during his encumbencie, but this to my hand was renewed, with this clauſe, <hi>To Officiate there notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the death of Mr. Cleaver;</hi> in this work I continued
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118367:6"/>with much gladneſs, and delight in the Lord, <hi>who had appointed and called me of his grace thereunto,</hi> till ſome other and new offences aroſe <hi>(for it is neceſſary that offences be, but woe unto them by whom)</hi> for which cauſe and upon which account I was a while ſuſpended, by the Military power here (it being the firſt and the laſt exerciſe of it that way, as I have heard of in the land) that the doors were forcibly ſhut a while againſt me, and the whole town; ſo that the Church it ſelf, as they call it, was for a while, as by the Pope of old <hi>Excommunicate,</hi> till it was opened again by the endeavor and authority of that worthy and faithfull Gentleman
<note n="*" place="margin">Mr <hi>Holl.</hi>
                  </note> the Burgeſs of this place. This conflict being over, which yet continued long, and extended ſomewhat far, for the debate of it was through complaint againſt me had in the <hi>Great and high Council of State,</hi> in which interim I had opportunity a while, to viſit on the firſt day the Neighbour Towns, eſpecially on the morning, for it was agreed on for a while that I ſhould be deprived of the morning Exerciſe here; for it was judged it might be for the greater eſteem, honor, and uſe of the morning Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe in the <hi>Caſtle,</hi> which was a while upheld by ſome of the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows of <hi>Eaton,</hi> but not without an Order from (as they ſay) the <hi>Council of State,</hi> which at length centred, but did not long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, in Mr <hi>Lockier,</hi> who was not long after called away for a more publique and ſpecial ſervice of the <hi>State;</hi> ſo that had there not been a ſupply by me in the Town, there had been ſilence as to matter of preaching either in <hi>Caſtle</hi> or <hi>Town:</hi> in this I continued faithful to God, this Nation, and this place, but not in peace or quiet, <hi>ſave onely in my heart and life to God:</hi> for in this time it was agreed on, that the people ſhould come together to make choyce of a Vicar, who coming together more headily then ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedly (for <hi>their time</hi> was not yet) fixed on a certain man,
<note place="margin">Mr D.</note> who was, as they ſay, faulty, as to the <hi>State,</hi> and ſuffered, and doth ſuffer upon that account, a deprivation (as men ſpeak) of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual promotion; ſo that as they were diſappointed, ſo they did diſappoint them that ſet them upon the thing: ſo that upon the diſagreement they had among themſelves (as it fell out for <hi>Paul</hi> ſometimes) I had a further liberty among this people, though to my diſadvantage greatly, as to my outward eſtate, yet the <hi>Lord</hi> being in it, I had joy ſufficient for a recompence of all I had ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or ſhould ſuſtain in time to come. About this time, or a little
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118367:7"/>before, there was a Lecture begun in the Town, which was judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed meet to be the day before <hi>that</hi> I was aſſign'd and <hi>deſired to:</hi> I confeſs I ſuggeſted my willingneſs of the Neighbor-Preachers concurrence with me, which was a little after layd hold on both of them, and thoſe that particularly applyed themſelves to the thing, but ſo, as that <hi>I</hi> might be <hi>excluded,</hi> as was well agreed on among them, though an humble addreſs were made to them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either my knowledg before-hand, or deſire, and that by two of the <hi>moſt grave men</hi> of the Town;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr D.</hi> and <hi>Mr R.</hi>
                  </note> but the Preachers, having a man engaged (as they were engaged to him) to vote as they pleaſed, they gave
<note n="*" place="margin">The <hi>Gov.</hi>
                  </note> him the <hi>chair,</hi> that would have had it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a little <hi>before,</hi> to determine for them; it being indeed his deſign by them, the better to remove me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <p>AFter a while, and being often in their company, invited where they were, and reaſoning with them, <hi>as I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance and liberty given me inwardly in my heart of God,</hi> not ever intending in the leaſt degree, contention or ſtrife with them, or other; I at length writ as followeth to them, to which I had no Reply.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sir, In the behalf of</hi> God, <hi>his</hi> Church, <hi>this</hi> Nation, <hi>and in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular this</hi> Town <hi>and</hi> my ſelf, <hi>I deſire by this Aſſembly (in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and I hope in truth, the Miniſters of</hi> Chriſt) <hi>to be reſolved by the Word of</hi> God <hi>in this Enquiry:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Whether my forced ſilence in this place, as to the work I was converſant in, and excluſion from your Company in that work, be according to the Scriptures, and the minde of</hi> God <hi>there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This I humbly deſire for a double cauſe:</hi> 1. <hi>Becauſe if I ſhould be, and willingly abide, in</hi> Tranſgreſſion, <hi>it would be the damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my Soul.</hi> 2. <hi>Becauſe you cannot</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Which I ſpoke not as out of doubt, but to urge an anſwer from them.</note> 
                        <hi>poſſibly be conceived to be onely</hi> lookers on, <hi>but muſt needs be judged, if not</hi> promoters of, <hi>yet ſuch as</hi> conſent to, <hi>the ſilencing of me in this place, unleſs you declare your ſelves to the contrary: but if you have</hi> conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>this I lay at your feet, begging you to ſhew cauſe by the</hi> Word of God, <hi>why; that if I am in an error, I may by</hi> the Grace of God <hi>be Revoked.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Yours in the Truth of our</hi> Saviour, R. BACON.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118367:7"/>
               <p> It was not long after this, but there was an endevor to invite, and bring in, ſometimes one, and ſometimes another of the <hi>Lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers,</hi> and at length the broad Seal was got, and 5 <hi>li.</hi> (more then ever was given, I think, for a Biſhops Licenſe) payd by a very forward Gentleman of the Town, one (as will anon appear) more haſty in his undertakements, then <hi>beleeving</hi> or <hi>ſucceſſful,</hi> though in this they ſay his wiſdom hath ſecured him, for he hath got his mony again of our <hi>body corporate:</hi> This undertakement failing, rather through the ill accommodation and undeſire of the people, then by any endevor of mine to oppoſe it, it hath been, upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thoughts of me, <hi>which they ſay are beſt,</hi> agreed on at length I ſhould take my turn, which, as not being aſhamed of my Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, rather then of a willing mind otherwiſe, I yeelded to: In this I have been <hi>thrice</hi> only in their hearing, and have at leaſt appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, and I hope in truth, ſome acceptance with them, which I deſire not for mine own ſake, ſo much as theirs, leſt they ſhould become guilty of diſowning <hi>the Love of God, which is true in me to them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV.</head>
               <p>THeſe things I have written briefly, as Introductory to that which followeth, theſe being onely <hi>the wounds I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the houſe of my friends, for my Mothers Children have been all along</hi> more or leſs <hi>offended with me:</hi> But as it was ſaid of the <hi>Lord</hi> to <hi>Jeremiah, If in the Land of Peace, wherein thou truſtedſt, they wearyed thee, or were an offence to thee, How wilt thou do in the ſwellings of Jordan?</hi> for behold the <hi>Tide</hi> is turn'd among us, and we are as it were on a ſudden <hi>as We Were</hi> before this War began, I mean, as to attainment in the <hi>matters of God:</hi> The people that have been in a ſort theſe many years <hi>aſleep,</hi> unleſs only in ſome <hi>few heads</hi> of them, to their <hi>loſs</hi> and <hi>prejudice,</hi> are anew <hi>awake</hi> among us, ſome ſay, by the ſound of the late Act of Pardon: Theſe people are ſo many and ſtrong, I mean in their <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves</hi> and purpoſes, as well as in their Actings among us, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>God</hi> help, as I am ſure he will his people, we ſhall all be, if not in other things, at leaſt in Religion <hi>(which as it is in God, is after all this ado about it of leaſt eſteem with men,)</hi> I ſay again, we ſhall be <hi>in ſtatu quo priùs:</hi> for they ſay, <hi>volens nolens, vi &amp;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118367:8"/>armis, per fas nefaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>,</hi> we will have what we will have; the day's our own, who ſhall withſtand us in the way we have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed on among our ſelves to <hi>take?</hi> This being of me diſcerned, I minded them openly of the prayer and requeſt of <hi>Hoſea,</hi> which is indeed the requeſt of the true <hi>Church</hi> in all ages, concerning the <hi>falſe, Give them O God; what wilt thou give them? give them a miſcarrying womb, and dry breſts:</hi> of this they had ſome <hi>ſenſe,</hi> though they uſually ſay, of what they hear of me, they have no <hi>knowledg.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <p>WHerefore a little after we had a ſolemn meeting of the people, which they call a <hi>Veſtry,</hi> having made all ready before-hand, both as to perſons and purpoſes, at which by the <hi>will of God</hi> I was, at which they had, as in effect they did expreſs, as no expectation, ſo no deſire: much reaſoning and debate they had as to the power by which I ſtood among them; I thought only to mind them of, and content my ſelf with declaring this, That the authority by which I ſtood was the ſame by which <hi>I am,</hi> even that of <hi>the grace of God:</hi> Wherefore, ſaid I, ſith we profeſs our ſelves, as we do, <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> let us together in ſobriety, calling upon the <hi>Name of God,</hi> having too the Bible among us, make tryal of the warrant by the work I have been hitherto taken up with; but they wav'd this diſcourſe, being indeed altogether <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit</hi> for it, as it appeared by the uncivil and <hi>rude</hi> behavior of ſome at that meeting. Wherefore an Order I muſt produce in all haſte, which as I neither then had by me, ſo neither did they meet for that <hi>intent;</hi> but what they came for, they did at that time <hi>fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate themſelves,</hi> which was the ſubſcribing a Petition, already drawn, for a Vicar; for a Vicar they muſt needs have, what ever came of the <hi>Truth among them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI.</head>
               <p>WHat in words they did expreſs, that they had in their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, That they were in very <hi>great diſtreſs,</hi> for (the more is the pity) <hi>food</hi> (poor people) for their ſouls, even altogether in ſuch another condition, as the <hi>mixt multitude</hi> were ſaid to be,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118367:8"/>when they <hi>wept again</hi> for the <hi>fleſh,</hi> and other the <hi>fiſh,</hi> and the like good things they before had in <hi>Aegypt;</hi> but now their <hi>Soul</hi> was <hi>dryed up,</hi> and nothing left but <hi>this Manna,</hi> whereof <hi>they had no knowledg,</hi> for the <hi>colour of it</hi> was and is like <hi>Bdelium,</hi> that it dazled their eyes to look on it, yea they were (they are) not able to look upon it <hi>at all:</hi> beſides, before it become <hi>food,</hi> it will coſt them not a little <hi>labor,</hi> for it muſt be either ground in a <hi>mill,</hi> or <hi>pound</hi> in a <hi>mortar,</hi> and after all <hi>baked</hi> well in an <hi>even,</hi> before there can be any taſte or true <hi>reliſh</hi> of it, as they well know, whoſe dayly <hi>food</hi> it is; for which cauſe it's wholly diſliked among us, that the people are fain to go for the bread that's for their tooth, ſome to one place, ſome to another; ſome to old <hi>Windſor,</hi> where doubtleſs they meet with many a good meal of <hi>onyons</hi> &amp; <hi>garlick,</hi> the ſavor of which is manifeſt every where among them; others, or the ſame at another time, to <hi>Dotchet</hi> or <hi>Cluet,</hi> concerning which perſons and people I will onely ſay this, That a man may ſufficiently, that hath any diſcerning of the things that differ, take knowledg of the <hi>Prieſt</hi> by the <hi>people,</hi> or, which is in effect the ſame, the <hi>people</hi> by the <hi>Prieſt</hi> they <hi>adore:</hi> for without all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure, neither of all theſe three (call them what you will, <hi>Parſons, Vicars,</hi> or <hi>Curates)</hi> are of ſuch attainment, either in point of knowledg or any good and vertuous life, that they ſhould have ſo many followers of them, unleſs it be for the cauſe above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. Wherefore, as I was concerned, as ſometimes <hi>Moſes</hi> was, I declared, that for their good I would wholly <hi>deny,</hi> as much as in me was, what they did with ſuch <hi>eagerneſs</hi> endevor after, even as a father hath no regard, but is rather ſeemingly <hi>cruel</hi> to the <hi>childe</hi> he loves, when he deſires, though with importunity, not <hi>bread,</hi> but a <hi>ſtone,</hi> not <hi>fiſh</hi> but a <hi>ſcorpion,</hi> a ſnake, a poyſonous hurtful thing: yet their importunity at length, which was ſo great, that I confeſs I was aſhamed (as the Prophet ſpake ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in alike caſe) that I conſented by ſuch a time to produce the Order, as I had it, for my being there, which I have had, as to this place, now theſe five years, a Copy of which I got for mony, and accordingly at the appointed time it was read among them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:118367:9"/>
               <head>SECT. VII.</head>
               <p>AT which, things were for a while <hi>huſh</hi> and <hi>ſtill,</hi> when upon a ſudden news was brought that one Mr <hi>Woodſon</hi> had chanced on a man for the <hi>turn of all the reſt;</hi> at which, though ſome ſeemed offended, yet after a ſight of him he proved in their eye, as the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſomewhere ſpeaks, a <hi>deſirable young man;</hi> worthy of; and therefore it was reported that he had the great <hi>Seal</hi> of <hi>England</hi> for this place, but it proved not true, neither then nor as yet, onely they ſay they have a good minde to the thing, and ſome hope of it; however he had enough to bring him here, throgh doubtleſs the importunity and ſolicitation of that <hi>woman</hi> ſpoken of in the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> that led aſide <hi>the young man to his hurt,</hi> as he will it may be in time finde; but he having no <hi>authority,</hi> I could not, I would not, give him my conſent to ſtand in my ſtead.</p>
               <p>At this ſecond meeting, when I was by promiſe engaged to give them a view of the paper, by which I had warrant, as to this work, from the <hi>Nation;</hi> And having conſidered, and indeed ſpoken before-hand, that this <hi>formality</hi> and <hi>tradition,</hi> which I could have wiſh'd to have been removed as a ſtumbling block out of the way of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> long ere this, I mean the <hi>Vicaridg,</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this place, that I ſay not in the whole Land, a ſeed of <hi>ſtrife</hi> among the people: as a Caſe of Conſcience I propoſed this to the people then <hi>aſſembled,</hi> and in particular had ſome long debate with our late <hi>Knight</hi> Mr <hi>Richard Bream</hi> about it, he contending in effect, that pretence of Conſcience was a ground and <hi>ſeed</hi> of much trouble and evil in a Land, which is true, unleſs we come to ſome certain <hi>Rule</hi> for the well guiding and right regulating of it; for we that profeſs our ſelves <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ought in all things to have the <hi>conſent</hi> and allowance of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>his Son our Saviour,</hi> in all we undertake: Wherefore Conſcience being nothing elſe then to concur with another in knowledg or conſent, as the word <hi>Conſcientia</hi> doth denote, it's neceſſary, and cannot be but that all men have warrant and ground for what they are and do, either <hi>of</hi> or <hi>from God,</hi> or <hi>his</hi> and our <hi>adverſary</hi> the <hi>Devil,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently have in all things either a good or an evil Conſcience; which <hi>good Conſcience,</hi> that I might retain, and the people with me in this place, I propounded to them, and a Gentleman that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118367:9"/>that ſtood by read this Propoſal, which being of no regard with them, I preſented it, as followeth, by one, to the reſt of the Preachers there.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="proposal">
                  <body>
                     <head>To the Reverend Preachers <hi>combined</hi> in a Lecture at <hi>New-Windſor.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Much honored men, For as much as it is preached, profeſſed, and beleeved, that you are ſuch with whom the</hi> Word of God <hi>(i. e.) his</hi> minde, is, <hi>as the Apoſtle ſaith,</hi> but we have the mind of Chriſt: <hi>It is humbly deſired (becauſe it muſt need be judged that you are concerned) to give Reſolution to this Demand, now in debate among us in this place:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Whether (as it is acknowledged</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">As it was of all the people.</note>
                        <hi>) if all things done amongst this people (by him that's yet among them) be according to</hi> God <hi>and the</hi> Scriptures, <hi>the ſaid people ought to be (for a Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or Tradition not approved in the Bible) countenanced to oppoſe the ſame, or make the ſame voyd unto themſelves,</hi> ſith no good thing can be oppoſed unto it ſelf, and no evil thing ought of good men or beleeving to be allowed ſo to do; <hi>both which are enforced from that ſaying of our Saviour,</hi> He that is not with us is againſt us, and he that gathereth not with us ſcattereth.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This was, as far as I could hear, put up in the pocket of him that received it
<note n="*" place="margin">Mr <hi>W.</hi>
                  </note>, as likewiſe was the former, and communicated to none of the reſt, at leaſt ſo as I could hear of it again.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
               <p>UPon this all was <hi>huſh</hi> again a while, at leaſt as to appearance, though a ſtrong endevor, but ſecret, ſtill they had to obtain their end, the <hi>man</hi> they had ſo great a liking to, who at length ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared at <hi>Windſor,</hi> with a brute of his having a recommendation, ſome ſaid from Mr <hi>Holland,</hi> others from the Lord <hi>Whitlock;</hi> but neither proved true, as himſelf confeſſed, coming to my lodging with two of the then <hi>Church-Wardens,</hi> who with great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity deſired my allowance of his preaching the next day, to which I promiſed within a little while at the Gentlemans lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to give him my anſwer, and deſired them after ſome diſcourſe to ſuſpend it till then; accordingly I came, and after ſome ſpeech
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118367:10"/>had with him of the <hi>Colledg</hi> of which we both were, as he ſaith, he knowing me, though I have no true remembrance of him, I told him, as I had purpoſed, that I was content to hear him to morrow, not onely <hi>once,</hi> but <hi>twice;</hi> wherefore I would he ſhould in the morning read a Chapter, and give as he was able the minde and ſcope of it, and as I and the <hi>Congregation liked it,</hi> he ſhould preach in the afternoon as I in the morning, and I would read: To this he ſomewhat ſolemnly replyed, That he was ſorry he had not had before-hand <hi>knowledg</hi> of my <hi>deſire,</hi> for then he would have <hi>prepared</hi> himſelf for <hi>the thing:</hi> To this I ſaid, I did not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own the uſe of <hi>reading books,</hi> and other means, but this I would ſay, as our Saviour doth, <hi>Every</hi> Scribe inſtructed <hi>to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven, brings forth out of his treaſury things both now and old;</hi> ſo that a good man, much more a good <hi>teacher,</hi> is more or leſs <hi>always ready;</hi> but this he liked not, for which he would appeal to the judgment and cenſure of all the moſt <hi>orthodox</hi> and <hi>learned men</hi> of <hi>this age,</hi> and in particular mentioned the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Mr <hi>Owen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr <hi>Owen.</hi>
                  </note> whom he ſerved a while, he ſays, at his Cure in his abſence in <hi>Ireland:</hi> but I beleeving Mr <hi>Owen</hi> of the ſame minde with me in this thing, told him, that ſurely what I ſaid could not be denyed, upon good grounds, of any; and therefore told him, that upon that alone account of his expounding after this manner, as we ſpeak, <hi>ex tempore,</hi> I would conſent to his preaching here, or otherwiſe not <hi>at all;</hi> for who is it (ſaid I) that is notable, and may not get a Sermon ready to ſay <hi>by rot</hi> upon all occaſions? Wherefore I adviſed him to be in good earneſt, for if he <hi>came not in the Name of God, I would not, I ſhould not ſay</hi> Amen <hi>to what he ſaid:</hi> at which he was not a little offended, for, ſaid he, <hi>I preach the Truth;</hi> at which I replyed, that the <hi>Truth</hi> is one thing, and the <hi>ſhadow, form,</hi> and <hi>picture</hi> of it another; now where the former is not, the latter cannot be as it ſhould; but he would not, he ſaid, learn of me: To which I replyed, that he that is not willing to learn <hi>even of the meaneſt,</hi> is not (as I judg, though I would not offend) meet or fit to <hi>teach any,</hi> unleſs you be of any greater attainment then was <hi>Paul.</hi> By this diſcourſe I had acquitted my ſelf before the <hi>Lord in my heart,</hi> and was at once eaſed of the <hi>burthen</hi> of him, and the whole Town, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore upon that account lay heavy upon me; for upon theſe terms he parted, ſo that I thought we ſhould have had his company no
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118367:10"/>more: late in the Evening came again our two <hi>Church-Wardens</hi> to minde me that the Gentleman was now willing to expound, ſo he might preach immediately after; but I gave them no other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer then before: wherefore after ſome menacing of me, that if there were any diſturbance I ſhould bear the blame, <hi>(though you indeed make it,</hi> ſaid I,) for he ſhould preach, ſaid they, whether I would or no; which indeed the next morning came to paſs accordingly, for I coming ſomewhat ſooner then uſual to the place of meeting, found the people ſpeeding thither, and our new Vicar forcing himſelf, without any kinde of power warrantable, to the accuſtomed place of ſpeaking, where when I ſaw him, I confeſs I was offended, and therefore (there nothing of ſervice being yet begun) I went up to the <hi>pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit</hi> to him, and told him, <hi>Sir, methinks you do very boldly to thruſt your ſelf upon the people, having no allowance either from Heaven, or of Men:</hi> He told me he had the warrant of the <hi>Church-Wardens;</hi> To whom I replyed, it was no leſs <hi>preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in them:</hi> where I left him in poſſeſſion quiet enough, unleſs it were in his <hi>own ſpirit,</hi> though he hath ſince, againſt the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his <hi>own heart,</hi> given out a report, I ſhould in a ſort aſſault him there, and lay hands on his cloke, as though I would <hi>per force</hi> have pull'd him out thence by the <hi>head</hi> and <hi>ſhoulders:</hi> Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for this, as I had no minde, as well as I had no warrant, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had I, or have, ſtrength to ſuch a <hi>beaſtly brutiſh buſineſs,</hi> it is enough that <hi>God is with me,</hi> the ſecurity <hi>of that Word and mind of his, is committed to me;</hi> for ſure it ſeems much more becoming a <hi>Christian,</hi> then a Heathen, to profeſs, as <hi>Horace</hi> did, <hi>Non egit Mauri jaculis nec arcu, integer vitae, ſceleriſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> purus.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Who faultleſs is, and <hi>walks with God,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Needs not, as <hi>others,</hi> uſe the rod.</l>
               </q>
               <p>My beſt ſtrength, through grace, is the doing <hi>in Chriſt</hi> the moſt <hi>holy Will</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> wherefore I retired my ſelf to a place conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for a hearing of what would be ſaid, and made obſervation eſpecially of theſe two things in his diſcourſe, he endevoring after the acceptance of the people, though it were to the prejudice of <hi>the moſt holy Word and truth of God;</hi> The firſt was his bending his ſpeech to a juſtification of the <hi>obſervation of days and times,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially according to the form and cuſtom of the late much-talk'd of <hi>Church of England,</hi> for which intent, according to the <hi>rubrick,</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:118367:11"/>were the Chapters read, and his diſcourſe thereon, aſſuring, That as ſuch things were of old in the firſt and beſt times, ſo they ought of good Chriſtians to be with no leſs <hi>eſteem respected now;</hi> not conſidering either the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> that hath been now yet of a long time, nor yet the expreſs forbidding of the Apoſtle the Church of the New Teſtament, as it is <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. and <hi>Col.</hi> 2. The ſecond was his <hi>Charity miſtaken,</hi> that all were to be reckoned of the <hi>brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi> (for that was his ſubject, <hi>Love the Brotherhood</hi>) that had the outward <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> a very quick and eaſie way of uniting all Opinions of men, all <hi>Europe</hi> and the World over; for if the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood be alone upon that account, I may truly ſay there is no ſuch thing at all, as that of which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaks; but the truth is, the <hi>world,</hi> or which is all one, the <hi>Synagogue of Satan,</hi> whether in <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>England,</hi> have, for a deceiving of themſelves and others, the more ſecurely and without controul poſſeſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as <hi>Babylon</hi> did of old, of theſe and the like moſt <hi>holy uten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſils,</hi> or <hi>veſſels of the Temple,</hi> or <hi>true Church of God;</hi> ſo that he that deſcribes the <hi>Brotherhood</hi> by any ſuch like outward obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is to me a ſure ſign that he hath little or no skill of the thing of which he ſpeaks, for as much as theſe things are found with much more glory in <hi>Babel,</hi> then any where elſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IX.</head>
               <p>BY this Sermon, the people of this place had again <hi>a taſte</hi> of that, which their Souls have theſe many years much luſted af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but have been of <hi>God and Man</hi> in a great degree deprived of, yet in this encounter the matter was, through a croſs endevor of other the people of this place, almoſt as ſoon at an end as begun, for they by Letter to Mr <hi>Holland,</hi> as the other by Petition to the Lord <hi>Whitlock,</hi> gave occaſion of a debate in private <hi>above,</hi> of the matters were more publique <hi>here,</hi> in ſo much that their expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion became for the preſent wholly fruſtrate, as to this <hi>man</hi> and <hi>meats;</hi> yea ſome there were, undeſired of me, though not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my knowledg, thought good to put an end to the ſtrife ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in this place, as touching the formality, name, and title of <hi>Vicar;</hi> for as for the thing it ſelf, the matter of <hi>preaching,</hi> and the officiating in all things relating <hi>to the glory of God,</hi> and the <hi>good of the people,</hi> as the <hi>Parliament</hi> by their Authority have allowed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118367:11"/>and continued me here, ſo I have with all gladneſs, as to the <hi>Lord</hi> and them, been faithful in the thing and truſt have been commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to me, according to the meaſure of <hi>Gods grace and preſence with me, which is indeed the rule according to which I walk:</hi> I ſay, there was upon this occaſion, by the conſent of ſome for this intent, this Letter writ to the Burgeſs of, and for this place, Mr <hi>Holland,</hi> the import of which I have been of many of all ſorts, almoſt ever ſince the death of Mr <hi>Cleaver,</hi> much urged to accept of, but ſtill refuſed upon this alone account that the matter need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not, for it could add nothing to the thing I was converſant in, ſaving onely a certain fooliſh, and ſome ſay, <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> name, which I was not willing, after all this <hi>war</hi> and <hi>trouble</hi> and ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle about matters of this nature, to accept; yet now at length through <hi>importunity,</hi> and the conſideration that <hi>as it could add nothing to me, ſo it could indeed derogate nothing from me, for let men call me what they pleaſe, I ſhall notwithſtanding through the help of God remain ſtill the ſame;</hi> as upon a like occaſion being ſometimes asked of one of the now chief Fellows of <hi>Eaton Colledg,</hi> whether it were lawful to be a Fellow there yea or no, I gave him onely this anſwer, <hi>that ſet a light, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a Candle, or the like, in the dark Cellar, or elſewhere, it will afford light</hi> as <hi>freely there</hi> as <hi>in the Chamber,</hi> for <hi>certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Motto of every good man is,</hi> as <hi>his</hi> was, <hi>ſemper idem,</hi> the <hi>ſame in one condition and place, as another:</hi> I ſay, upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count I conſented to the writing and ſubſcribing this Letter in the words and form following.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Very worthy Sir,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">A Letter to M. <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>We are encouraged again the ſecond time to preſent to you our deſire as concerning Mr</hi> Bacon, <hi>that hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing had an experience of</hi> his manner of life, purpoſe, faith, doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, <hi>and</hi> diligence <hi>in the work he</hi> delights in, <hi>and we by him</hi> partake of, <hi>we have judged our ſelves</hi> concerned, <hi>and do in a manner fully perſwade and aſſure our ſelves of your further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of us in this endevor, that the</hi> Broad-ſeal, <hi>ſought for ſo often for others, might be through your means and our charge fixed now at length on him, not becauſe he of himſelf either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires or needs it, for a juſtification of him, or the work he labors in, but rather firſt to put an end to the ſtrife is already here upon that account; and ſecondly, thereby is conceived hope of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118367:12"/>perfecting of the</hi> good is by him, <hi>through the help of</hi> God <hi>alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy begun; and finally, it is conceived</hi> worthy of the State and you, <hi>and</hi> this place, <hi>to fix him to this place with ſuitable</hi> encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, <hi>that hath to his outward prejudice, ſo faithfully and ſo long ſerved the</hi> Lord and you among us: <hi>This if you procure, we ſhall acknowledg our ſelves further bound to you; and for that cauſe are bold to ſubſcribe our ſelves,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your humble ſervants and friends, to ſerve you in the</hi> Lord, <hi>at</hi> Windſor.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This was after a while ſeconded by the voluntary offer and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devor of one of the chief men of our Town, who took oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity at his being in <hi>London</hi> to apply himſelf both to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Holland</hi> and the Lord <hi>Whitlock,</hi> from both which he had, as he did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, encouragement as to my <hi>continuance here;</hi> onely this they were pleaſed to ſay, as well the one as the other, <hi>that they did judg it meet not to burthen me with any ſuch thing, as the name and title of Vicar,</hi> yet not expreſſing themſelves as willing of Mr <hi>Kind's</hi> coming, to a concurrence with me.</p>
               <p>About the ſame time I had occaſion in <hi>London</hi> (coming not at any time there meerly upon the account of this buſineſs, to which this diſcourſe doth relate) Mr <hi>Holland</hi> (which I crave leave of him to make publique) profeſt it was his Judgment (as it was and is, I am ſure, my deſire) <hi>that this Name and Title of</hi> Vicar <hi>may be in the Land wholly at an end, as indeed it is high time it ſhould:</hi> at this I confeſs I was not a little glad, for it ſeemed ſomewhat ſtrange, and a matter indeed much to be lamented, <hi>That after all this ado,</hi> and <hi>turning as a door upon the hinge, we ſhould be found both in form and practice, not one</hi> Iota <hi>moved, from what we were ten years ago.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>SECT. X.</head>
               <p>HAving had this account given me, I returned, as heretofore, with delight and diligence, to the work I was concerned in, and as I remember was in particular engaged to the Tueſday Lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, where I confeſs I appeared, though few were there to hear me: I will not refuſe to make mention of the Text which I judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed meet to be minded, eſpecially in the times that now are,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118367:12"/>
                  <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.18. <hi>I will gather them that are ſorrowful for the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Aſſembly, thoſe that are of thee, to whom the reproach of it was and is a burthen:</hi> At this diſcourſe ſome offence was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, but alone of the Preachers, for opening that of <hi>Solomons Song,</hi> as I did, Chap. 3. v. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. eſpecially Verſ. 7. <hi>That the Spouſe never found her Beloved till ſhe had gone one ſtep be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Watchmen, of whom ſhe ſought him, but found him not.</hi> Verily I was <hi>greatly moved</hi> and <hi>grieved</hi> in my <hi>heart,</hi> that they ſhould take offence at this; for without all doubt ſuch as they are ſhould not <hi>ſeek their own, but the honor of him they ſay have ſent them,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>the Lord himſelf;</hi> which gave me occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to remember and preſent the ſpeech of that old dying, but wicked Biſhop in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> time, when one it ſeems preſſed in ſpirit ſaid to him, <hi>Doubtleſs it were better that the Scriptures were allowed in Engliſh,</hi> replyed with ſome heat, <hi>If that door were once open, then indeed farewell all;</hi> as though nothing were <hi>more prejudicial to the Clergy, then the knowledg of the People:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">At the houſe of Mr <hi>Bream.</hi>
                  </note> At this meeting I came, being particularly invited thereto, which is, I confeſs, the rule I have hitherto walked by, as to thoſe enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XI.</head>
               <p>WIthin a little while after this, I had occaſion and was bent in my heart for the Weſt, not onely ſo much for the cauſe of other matters, as <hi>to have a renewed taſte of the fruit I hoped, and have much longed after, to partake of among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, with whom I have had my converſation in times paſt, upon the account of the teſtimony of the Coming and hope of our moſt dear Lord and Saviour:</hi> Among them I was <hi>a while with great delight, finding them in full expectation of what was much in my heart, the dawning of the Day of God,</hi> and <hi>their gathering toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one in him, upon that account.</hi> Before I undertook this, I had ſome promiſe of ſupply of one ſuitable to me, and known and much deſired of the moſt <hi>enlightened of the people in this place;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr <hi>S.</hi>
                  </note> but to make it yet more ſure, I endeavored with ſome of our Neighbors at <hi>Eaton,</hi> whom I have with a ready minde hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſerved upon the like occaſion, that in my abſence, if they thought meet, they would ſtand in my ſtead: but having no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118367:13"/>I could not aſſure my ſelf of any; wherefore, as upon the account aforeſaid, <hi>viz.</hi> my longing after the people in the Weſt, as alſo becauſe of my <hi>aſſiduity</hi> and <hi>diligence</hi> among the people here (<hi>unthankfully,</hi> that I ſay no more at preſent, <hi>entertained</hi> of them) I reſolved to take the opportunity, and leave the event and guidance of the matter and people to <hi>God himſelf</hi> alone, the great <hi>Shepherd</hi> of the ſheep, <hi>in whoſe cuſtody alone I am ſure we are all ſafe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XII.</head>
               <p>YEt being as far as <hi>Newport</hi> and <hi>Cardiff</hi> in <hi>Wales,</hi> I was of <hi>the Lord,</hi> after the ſecond Sabbath, ſtrongly <hi>moved in my heart</hi> to return, ſo as to be at <hi>Windſor</hi> on the third, which was the time, is as yet call'd <hi>Eaſter-day; for we have in the Land, as yet, ſo little of the ſubſtance, that we are fain ſtill, and do with much zeal, as elſewhere, ſo especially here, retain, not the Jewiſh, by no means, forſooth, that muſt be ſaid, yet it cannot be denyed but that we hold faſt to the Popiſh new-invented Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh, as well as the Heathen types and ſhadows.</hi> In my abſence they were deſtitute of one to fill the Pulpit the firſt day; on the ſecond they got with much endeavor, having a fit opportunity, Mr <hi>Kind,</hi> having been all this while as it were to this place <hi>faſt aſleep,</hi> but he is awake of them, and brought with all ſpeed here, when (doubtleſs upon conſultation had one with another) he gave notice of a Sacrament ſhould be on the next day, (ſure as a ſeal of <hi>that union of theirs, which was not, is not, in God,)</hi> for which intent all things, <hi>at leaſt without them,</hi> were made ready, the Innen waſh'd, and the plate and other utenſils made bright for the purpoſe, and the wine beſpoke, becauſe ſuch as they would have was not ready, for they muſt needs have Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kadine, there was to be ſomething, at leaſt like it, made of the Vintner that week; at the end of which, I unlooked for, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcom as to theſe people, came; ſome ſaying, I was ſent for, and came <hi>poſt-haſte,</hi> though I had no intimation, ſaving <hi>onely in my heart from above,</hi> neither was it poſſible I ſhould: Wherefore others, that were as glad of my return, likened it ſomewhat to the <hi>man Moſes his coming down from the Mount, when in his abſence Aaron and the people had agreed to make them a Calf in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118367:13"/>ſtead of God in Chriſt, to go before them:</hi> Hence there was not a little ado and talk of the people, ſome adviſing, and they none of the meaneſt of them, to defer it (at leaſt) to another time; others were as much reſolved, have it they would now, what ever it coſt them! I hearing this on the next day minded to have ſent to the Mayor, or rather to have come unto him, and to have got ſome five or ſix more of the chief of the Town to have conferred together, to prevent any inconvenience that might hereby ariſe; and for that intent the chief man in this cauſe, as to activeneſs, came to me into a place in town, to which I ſent for him, and told him my reſolve; wherefore we going together, he indeed unwillingly, but <hi>I</hi> of a ready mind,
<note place="margin">Rand.</note> to an ancient man and Profeſſor, but he not being within, ſome ſay willingly, I was urged to go to, and ſpeak with the Steward, but ſtaying a while in the ſtreet, he being calld, came to me, with whom after a little diſcourſe I abruptly (I confeſs) left him, he calling in queſtion that which <hi>was to me certain,</hi> and <hi>I am perſwaded to him alſo in his heart;</hi> By all which I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood an agreement was already made, and backed by all the power they had or could (but ſecretly) make, to meet the next day <hi>to the purpoſe</hi> aboveſaid: wherefore on the morrow I came ſomewhat timely, willing not to be prevented as I was before, I found the doors ſhut, but within a while came the Sextons boy, and told me the Churchwardens had ſecured the keys, that the doors could not be opened till they came; wherefore ſtaying a while there, not a few perſons of very rude and unbecoming behavior came neer, <hi>reproaching</hi> and <hi>reviling me</hi> openly to my face, one of them at length ſwearing, <hi>but not in truth,</hi> that what ever come of it, they would I <hi>ſhould have nought to do there that day,</hi> for however it was with me, yet their conſcience was to do as they ſaid: but ſaid I, is your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience <hi>well informed?</hi> to which was made this anſwer, <hi>they could not tell whether it were yea or no:</hi> at length came one more ancient then wiſe, <hi>whom God forgive,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>G.</hi>
                  </note> upbraiding me with teaching them what he ſaid they did not at all underſtand, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it were this, that I made them to be all either Jews or Gentiles, yea plainly telling me (as I remember ſome have ſaid of old they called the Diſciples firſt of all <hi>Chriſtians</hi> (i.e.) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (i. e.) <hi>Chriſts Aſſes,</hi> at <hi>Antioch,</hi> it being given (as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118367:14"/>is believed) as a name of reproach there) that I was one of the verieſt <hi>Aſſes</hi> that ever he knew, or to that purpoſe: <hi>Now O God, ſaid I in my heart, yea and tongue, this people talk of what they underſtand not, ſpeaking evil of what</hi> is the <hi>alone help and healing of them, the Lord and his love.</hi> The Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens coming and ſeeming to entreat my allowance of them, had in mean time at another door let in Maſter <hi>Kind</hi> to the Pulpit, where he no ſooner came, but he had his guard of <hi>rude men about him</hi> to ſecure him there; which when I had percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved I withdrew to a place convenient to hear, having a little before had occaſion to tell them, that ſure enough it was mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt they wanted what they could not deny was needful at ſuch a time as that, <hi>to wit, Love; or as it is rendered and now termed charity;</hi> they, I mean two of them that were Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens, for ſo they wil needs be called, though I am ſure they are <hi>no ſuch thing as the word imports,</hi> told me indeed that for that alone cauſe they purpoſed (as they ſaid) that day not to come to the Communion, meaning the <hi>Idol</hi> they had made rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to fall down <hi>to,</hi> and <hi>adore:</hi> For I had a little before told them, however they made boaſt of <hi>amity</hi> and <hi>love,</hi> it was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt enough they had <hi>none in their heart</hi> to afford me, which indeed they did not refuſe to confeſs; <hi>yet forſooth they could notwithſtanding pray, and do other things well enough pleaſing to God, though in mean time they remained profeſſedly in the hate of him in me, and me for his name ſake.</hi> After the leſſon read, by one that hath in like manner forced himſelf to that ſervice, I took my opportunity when there was ſome ſilence in the Congregation, to ſpeak as followeth, ſitting in the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery and ſeeing every thing carryed on there by <hi>force,</hi> through a manifeſt oppoſition againſt the <hi>authority both of God and man,</hi> as is evident and confeſt. I deſired the Preacher would give out to the people the minde and meaning of this text, and words of <hi>Samuel</hi> to <hi>Saul,</hi> which he ſpake upon his rebellion againſt <hi>God</hi> and <hi>him, To obey</hi> is better then <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> and to harken (as I am ſure they did not to <hi>God</hi>) then the <hi>fat of Rams;</hi> upon this one ſtood by, and ſaid I diſturbed the Congregation, others began to make a noiſe under the gallery, and our ſinging man calling to Maſter <hi>Kind</hi> to go on, which he did having yet no warrant either the one or the other, and might with as much
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118367:14"/>pretence poſſeſs the Caſtle, yea the whole Nation, to which it doth directly tend, and to which it muſt needs come in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, if it be <hi>thus</hi> let <hi>alone,</hi> but I held my peace; Sermon ended in the which was an exhortation to the Sacrament, which they had in their way, made ready for them, I went <hi>as the Lord knows in love</hi> to the Veſtry, where <hi>I</hi> no ſooner appeared but Maſter <hi>Kind</hi> as moved at my coming, being putting on his gown (which for the greater ſolemnity of the buſineſs he had brought down with him) <hi>for where the truth is not,</hi> it <hi>muſt be piec'c up with ſuch toyes as theſe,</hi> he demands of me, prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me, what <hi>I</hi> had to ſay to him? Why truly ſaid <hi>I,</hi> that you read over your text again, which was this, for an <hi>Eaſter</hi> days Sermon; <hi>Come ſee where the Lord lay:</hi> Now ſaid <hi>I,</hi> your text is not as you expounded it, an exhortation to come to <hi>Christ,</hi> much leſs <hi>to the Sacrament,</hi> unleſs in another ſenſe then you meant it, but that the women ſhould ſee, as the Diſciples did afterwards, that he was not in the <hi>Sepulchre,</hi> where they <hi>thought</hi> to have <hi>found him;</hi> now ſaid <hi>I,</hi> as your text led you, to <hi>ſhew where Chriſt is not, ſo if you be able to ſhew where he is, you ſay ſomething, or elſe you do nothing at all:</hi> at which he ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much moved, and would, he ſaid, diſpute with me about the matter before the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of <hi>Divines;</hi> diſtinguiſhing immediately upon our diſcourſe of the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> betwixt, as they ſay, <hi>Corpus Chriſti Sacramentale &amp; reale,</hi> profeſſing his knowledge and power only to meddle with the former, but having no ſence or perceiving of the latter: <hi>now the former without this latter is nought at all, ſpells nothing, is nothing, ſave a bare ſign or cypher which makes no number;</hi> Neither is there any Chriſtian, whether Popiſh or Proteſtant, <hi>Lutheran</hi> or <hi>Calviniſt</hi> that doth or ever did hold the <hi>Supper of the Lord</hi> to be a <hi>bare</hi> and <hi>only ſign;</hi> ſo that <hi>I</hi> might truly ſay the <hi>thing</hi> was not <hi>there,</hi> Chriſt was not there, of which he ſpake <hi>(i. e.)</hi> the <hi>Lord or his body,</hi> or which is all one, <hi>caena domini, the Supper of the Lord,</hi> which is <hi>no other</hi> then as <hi>himſelf</hi> ſaith, <hi>the daily, but ſuperſubſtantial and caeleſtial food of them that beleeve or are born from above:</hi> whileſt <hi>I</hi> had thus ſpeech with Maſter <hi>Kind,</hi> came in looking pale our Unknighted Gentleman, Maſter <hi>Bream,</hi> charging me with a diſturbing of the Congregation, and letting of the Preacher in the ſervice he was bound for, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118367:15"/>they both together multiplied in their <hi>unbelief</hi> and <hi>ignorance of God</hi> many words, oppreſſing me as much as they could with <hi>them;</hi> that <hi>I</hi> ſought out a place convenient, where to retire my ſelf, till their ſpeech ſhould have an end; but Mr. <hi>Bream</hi> denyed me that reſt which <hi>he</hi> could not give unto me, laying hold on my arms and cloak, and by force (<hi>I</hi> not much <hi>I</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs reſiſting) thruſt me out of doors; at which <hi>I</hi> ſaid in my heart, and not only ſo, <hi>What Communion Sir will you have, from which you will excommunicate me?</hi> He with much heat affirmed, the whole Town would agree together, and draw up <hi>Articles</hi> againſt me, as ſince <hi>I</hi> hear from him they have done: There followed many <hi>rude men</hi> after us, repeating and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying what the Gentleman ſaid; moreover he told me the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and boys of the ſtreet would <hi>ſtone me,</hi> and that Hereticks were wont worthily ſo to be dealt with, <hi>(of which number Sir, ſaid I, you remember holy Steven was one;)</hi> but <hi>I</hi> departed home, only telling him <hi>I</hi> was ſorry to ſee him in ſo great a paſſion. <hi>I</hi> perceive the number of Communicants were very few, they ſay (ſince) <hi>I</hi> was a let unto them, truly <hi>I</hi> did not appear upon that account, or for that end, but meerly ſith <hi>I</hi> ſaw they were <hi>heady</hi> and <hi>reſolved</hi> in the buſineſs, <hi>I</hi> thought it my duty <hi>to God</hi> and <hi>them,</hi> to take the opportunity to give them ſome <hi>light</hi> in what they <hi>did</hi> ſo <hi>headily</hi> and upon the alone account of <hi>cuſtom thruſt themſelves upon,</hi> even as the <hi>horſe that ruſheth into the battel.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:118367:15"/>
               <head>SECT. XIII.</head>
               <p>OF this I confeſs the next day I gave notice by letter to the Burgeſs of this place, yet my letter went by Boat, wherefore I could not, neither had I a thought of doing prejudice to any, as it was generally reported, I was the cauſe of Mr. <hi>Bream</hi> his ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for by a Meſſenger from the Councel of State that evening; yea one of our grave women (forſooth) very confidently reports,
<note place="margin">Mis. <hi>M.</hi>
                  </note> I was met in the returning from the great City, and told, that that had been my buſineſs there: this is like as true as is the report now freſh in Town, that there came a man at the Church door to ſpeak with me, but I admitted him not to it, who told one of our Neighbors, as <hi>ſtout</hi> as I was, I had taken of him above <hi>two hundred pounds</hi> for making of Hats for him, <hi>which I would it were true, I confeſs I would not refuſe the employment; for I am very well content (were I able) to work for my living as the Apoſtle was, yet ſhall not, cannot look back from the work I have been hitherto converſant in; but had it been for hire, I would have left it long agoe.</hi> About this time was <hi>reawakened</hi> a certain <hi>ſomthing,</hi> for what it is I cannot tell, produc't as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſo upon this occaſion, by one Mr. <hi>Baker,</hi> who <hi>were he as good</hi> as <hi>rich,</hi> might be of <hi>great uſe to this Town</hi> and <hi>Nation,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it ſeems, as I have been told, and is certainly true, procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of ſome of the late Aſſembly of Divines about the time of my firſt coming to this place, ſome kind of <hi>ſubſcribing,</hi> that I was not of <hi>them approved,</hi> as it ſeems this Gentleman was, and is, as very ſound <hi>to God and Man,</hi> both in his <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>life,</hi> as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears he had a great deal more <hi>favour with them then I;</hi> they would not otherwiſe have fortified <hi>ſuch a man</hi> againſt <hi>me:</hi> this note, or whatever it be, hath of him been made uſe of, if by any means, to alienate the people of all ſorts from me, in the which he hath not a little of late prevailed, many in the Town having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Copies of it, though I could never ſee any; yea, they have, as the people of <hi>like nature</hi> and <hi>ſpirit heretofore,</hi> ſought by all means, into all places, where I have been, to ſearch and find out the forepaſt hiſtory of my life, making ſpecial and particular uſe of my <hi>ſufferings</hi> at <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> yea at <hi>Oxford,</hi> when I was a youth there, as well as of the wrongs and loſſes I have ſuſtained
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118367:16"/>heretofore in the caſe of the Common-Prayer and Ceremonies from the Biſhops, <hi>ſo that the evil that was in them all, is riſen up and allowed here, or connived at, at</hi> Windſor, <hi>to the diſhonour of God, and the ſhame of the pretended high attainment of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in the things divine and of God;</hi> but whether this be under the hand of the Aſſembly, or of ſome of them, I cannot tell: this they know, that I refuſed not to come before them to a giving teſtimony of the <hi>truth.</hi> I believe, as they well know, the great matter they ſeemed to be offended with, was my non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking the Covenant, which I only refuſed as upon that occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as though it were even <hi>eſſential</hi> to the matter of <hi>preaching.</hi> Some other things they ſaid as to the <hi>Catechiſms;</hi> but all they took notice of as diſpleaſing them, as may appear afterwards, as <hi>unſound,</hi> was the buſineſs of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> which they ſay, as indeed <hi>I do, as to the outwardneſs of it, judg to be in eſteem with us of like nature, as are other outward rites and obſervations, not ſuch as in them conſists the Kingdom of Heaven, or the true knowledg of God:</hi> this was only mentioned as an error, in a little Book writ by thoſe convened at <hi>Sion Colledg,</hi> for detecting of the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed error and falſe Doctrine of many <hi>worthy men</hi> in the Land: 'tis true, Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> in a large Book of his ſeems offended, not only at it, but other paſſages; <hi>but the ſtory of the times, and the reproach cast of him upon others more eminent a thouſand fold then my ſelf, as the Lord General,</hi> Mr. <hi>Burton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Dell, &amp;c.</hi> may <hi>ſave me the labor of ſpeaking, as to the vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of my ſelf as to the Aſſembly:</hi> yet I will add what will give ſome hint of the offence, they have it ſeems taken at me <hi>viz.</hi> my being here without either their <hi>allowance</hi> or <hi>order,</hi> which yet was not through either my deſire or endeavour, as it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear partly by my being with them in conference from about <hi>two</hi> till after <hi>ſeven</hi> of the Clock; but alſo by the following letter written to Mr. <hi>Holland</hi> upon that occaſion, whereby may appear what eſteem the Authour of it had of the Aſſembly and me, in thoſe days.</p>
               <p>Sir, The Bearer hereof Mr. <hi>Bacon, is that good man</hi> which the Town hath choſen <hi>for this place,</hi> as you will underſtand further by a Letter from the Mayor and his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, Sir <hi>Robert Bennet,</hi> the Governour, and divers others: we doubt not of your beſt aſſiſtance, according to the Contents of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118367:16"/>the ſaid Letter: we have alſo written to Sir <hi>Henry Mildmay,</hi> hoping that both of you may ſo carry it, <hi>as to get him paſſed by the Committee, without any reference to the Aſſembly, &amp;c.</hi> Subſcribed your Servant in Chriſt <hi>John Bachiler. Windſor</hi> Caſtle, <hi>April</hi> 13. 1647. which it ſeems was done accordingly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIV.</head>
               <p>BUt the people to perfect their work of my, or rather the <hi>truths, remove far from them,</hi> it being <hi>Eaſter</hi> week, they choſe two others, but moſt falſly call'd Church wardens <hi>(rather truth and Church oppoſers, which is the pillar and ground of it)</hi> men much more for the purpoſe,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>M.</hi>
                  </note> theſe with others get hands not a few, ſome through fear, and ſome for advantage, as hath been confeſt of one eminent in the Town, <hi>though a Reed indeed ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with every wind,</hi> for the obtaining the man and Vicar they endeavour after, <hi>whoſe contention about him is like the ſtrife had of the people heretofore about their idol Maypole, for a May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pole they muſt have, and a Vicar theſe muſt have,</hi> nec poſſunt dicere quare, hoc tantum poſſunt dicere amo te, <hi>for their luſts ſake:</hi> this they proſecute at <hi>London,</hi> but had a preſent repulſe from the Burgeſs of the place; but yet have had, they <hi>hold all men in hand,</hi> no little encouragement from the Lord <hi>Whitlock,</hi> of whom they report they have his countenance, yea the promiſe of the great Seal, which yet as I do not believe, ſo I have cauſe to the contrary, as the teſtimony of Mr. <hi>Cokayn,</hi> whoſe abiding is in the ſame houſe with him: as likewiſe the Relation of the Lord <hi>Whitlock</hi> himſelf, not only to Mr. <hi>Holland,</hi> but alſo to a Gentleman of good note and account in this place, who went in particular to him upon this occaſion; yea it ſhould ſeem ſtrange, and indeed impoſſible, unleſs the Lord <hi>Whitlock</hi> ſhould be contrary to himſelf, to allow and permit any <hi>violence of the people to be uſed in any thing, leaſt of all in things of this nature,</hi> as the caſe is here; ſo the people do in profeſt oppoſition againſt the pretended, if not real endeavour of the Mayor, and the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er civil here, as it came to paſſe the next Sabboth day, or rather the third after it: the Preacher having in the morning with no little devotion, doubtleſs, prayed for the Right Worſhipful the Mayor, and the Worſhipful the Aldermen his Brethren; yea for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118367:17"/>the High Court of Parliament; and yet as I ſpake in the afternoon <hi>(when only theſe rude men allow me there)</hi> he not only himſelf did act, but profeſſedly allowed others in an oppoſition againſt the expreſs <hi>authority of both:</hi> wherefore I do confeſs I had with much <hi>ſtruggle</hi> at length obtain'd <hi>leave of God in my heart</hi> to appear again in that <hi>place,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> which ſeemed to me <hi>as moſt polluted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed,</hi> with the <hi>lies</hi> that <hi>flow out from thence to the deceiving of the whole Land:</hi> this I did not refuſe, when I came there to make known to the people, that then were preſent; <hi>I was holp in this thing of God,</hi> for <hi>through him I came to underſtand,</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I ſtood in the ſame place, yet I was not there upon the ſame <hi>account</hi> with <hi>him</hi> and <hi>others</hi> that ſpeak there, <hi>ſed non a Deo, but not from God:</hi> there were preſent at this diſcourſe, as I have been ſince told, <hi>two Parliament men,</hi> that ſeem, as Mr. <hi>Bream</hi> ſaith, much offended with what ever I <hi>ſaid</hi> or <hi>did</hi> at that time; they never heard (as he ſaith they ſay) ſuch <hi>expounding,</hi> ſuch <hi>preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> ſuch <hi>catechiſing,</hi> yea there was not (which it ſeems they <hi>earneſtly looked after</hi>) ſo much as a <hi>Pſalm.</hi> Now I confeſs, its ſufficient for me, to <hi>mind</hi> the work I am converſant in <hi>as to God,</hi> whether it <hi>take,</hi> and be <hi>accepted</hi> with <hi>men,</hi> yea or no: yet I have thought, whoever theſe <hi>Gentlemen</hi> were, for I know, neither their perſons or names, that though they had no great <hi>liking</hi> to other things, yet they ſhould very well <hi>reſent</hi> the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe I had to <hi>uphold</hi> and <hi>juſtifie</hi> the <hi>just</hi> power and authority of <hi>Parliament,</hi> whereof theſe were Members, unleſs <hi>as ſome would have I confeſs</hi> (as it hath been the caſe of the <hi>powers</hi> of the Nations of <hi>a long time</hi>) that the power of the Parliament whether <hi>ſubordinate</hi> or <hi>ſupream,</hi> ſhould only be <hi>manifeſt</hi> and <hi>made uſe</hi> of to the <hi>upholding of evil,</hi> both <hi>men and things and cuſtoms in the Land, rather then the good:</hi> I am ſure there is no <hi>exerciſe</hi> of it in this place at this time; as to the thing, I have been now theſe five years converſant in; the <hi>power,</hi> whether <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial</hi> or <hi>Civil,</hi> laying at the feet of rude men, who have and do beat all the <hi>ſway in this particular,</hi> to the great <hi>ſhame</hi> and <hi>reproach</hi> of the <hi>Government,</hi> not only of this <hi>place,</hi> but <hi>Nation:</hi> indeed they hold the people <hi>in hand,</hi> yea they have <hi>told me,</hi> and the <hi>Mayor</hi> of the Town, and Mr. <hi>Mills,</hi> that <hi>none have power in that place but the Church-wardens,</hi> they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118367:17"/>mean a power of <hi>force,</hi> that of <hi>Bulls</hi> and <hi>Bears:</hi> now theſe men may upon the ſame <hi>account</hi> make the <hi>Church a Castle,</hi> and <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Guns</hi> and <hi>Swords to ſecure themſelves in what ere they do,</hi> as <hi>ſet Ruffians</hi> there <hi>per force to rule:</hi> Indeed, as I once <hi>declared,</hi> even to <hi>the Mayor himſelf,</hi> that in the <hi>true Church</hi> the <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of one</hi> is as <hi>great</hi> as is the <hi>authority of another,</hi> there being <hi>acknowledged in it no other authority then that of the Word,</hi> which is the <hi>Scepter of Chriſt,</hi> by which its <hi>rul'd,</hi> not a <hi>power of Beaſts,</hi> or a <hi>beaſtly power</hi> of <hi>force,</hi> as theſe men like <hi>brutes,</hi> not either as <hi>men</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> lay claim unto, and have <hi>been</hi> and are <hi>allowed</hi> in.</p>
               <p>The next <hi>Sabboth</hi> was ſent down a letter from the <hi>Burgeſs</hi> of this place to the <hi>Mayor</hi> of the Town. A Copy of which I thought worthy here to expreſs.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand there is much</hi> diſturbance <hi>in the Town of</hi> Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, <hi>about</hi> preaching <hi>in the</hi> Church; <hi>and therefore I thought fit to write to you, to deſire you, that the</hi> peace may be kept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them by your Authority: <hi>That ſo he, that yet hath the</hi> ſole authority <hi>that I know of, to preach there, may not be</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd <hi>in the</hi> performance <hi>of his duty, who is</hi> Mr. Bacon, <hi>a man of a</hi> pious <hi>and</hi> peaceable Converſation, <hi>and ſo</hi> judged <hi>by all</hi> good men <hi>that</hi> know <hi>him, for ought I</hi> ever yet heard. <hi>And the</hi> Parliament <hi>by their</hi> Authority <hi>having appointed him to be</hi> Preacher there, <hi>I think it's</hi> your duty <hi>to ſee that he may</hi> peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably execute that which the Parliament hath directed him unto. <hi>Sir, I ſhall heartily deſire that all the people of the Town may have</hi> ſuch a teacher as may lead them into truth through the goodneſs of God. <hi>And wiſh they would</hi> quiet <hi>their own ſpirits until the</hi> Parliament <hi>ſhall ſettle ſuch a</hi> courſe <hi>both</hi> there <hi>and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in the Nation, as ſhall be I truſt</hi> for the glory of God, and good of all his, <hi>which they are endeavouring with all conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient ſpeed to do, and had ſooner done, if the publique preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Nation had permitted.</hi> Sir, <hi>I have no more at preſent, but to ſubſcribe my ſelf, Your very affectionate friend and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Cornelius Holland.</signed>
                        <dateline>Kinſington, <date>May 1. 1652.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This Letter being delivered on the evening of the Sabboth, the next morning as I paſſed by towards the publique place, Mr. <hi>Mills</hi> ſtanding at his door, deſired me to <hi>ſtep a little out of my
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118367:18"/>way;</hi> ſaid I, that I <hi>ſhall not do by any means,</hi> yet ſhall not refuſe to come to you, with whom I found the <hi>Mayor,</hi> who together told me of this <hi>Letter,</hi> and how they had <hi>endeavoured</hi> to the <hi>utmoſt, but could not</hi> (or <hi>rather without all peradventure</hi> would not) let or hinder the people from their rude reſolved purpoſe, <hi>confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> they were greatly <hi>aſhamed,</hi> yea that it was the <hi>ſhame</hi> of the Town and place, that ſuch <hi>violence</hi> of <hi>rude men</hi> ſhould be <hi>ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed:</hi> the <hi>Mayor</hi> went before, and I came immediately after and found Mr. <hi>Kind</hi> in the <hi>Pulpit</hi> with his guard of rude men at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending him, among whom when I appeared, and the Mayor, they looking pale, I fear with <hi>wrath</hi> and <hi>envy,</hi> being reſolved, as it came from the mouth of one of them, to have <hi>laid hands</hi> on me, the Mayor entreated them, but left his <hi>Mace and his heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind;</hi> but they knew his <hi>mind,</hi> and their <hi>other Rulers too,</hi> though they did pretend ſome of them to ſome other thing: I askt them what theſe rude people meant, they told me they came there to hear, nay rather to diſturb, and if need be, to <hi>fight,</hi> to maintain their <hi>luſt and evil;</hi> ſome <hi>threatned,</hi> others <hi>perſwaded me</hi> by <hi>all means to leave theſe parts, for they had no deſire of my company.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This day I went to <hi>Eaton,</hi> and heard a good and ſeaſonable diſcourſe there, I beſeech God they may make <hi>good uſe of it;</hi> in the afternoon I ſpake ſomewhat large by way of expoſition on the 3. <hi>of Jam:</hi> eſpecially on theſe two <hi>heads, Brethren be not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Maſters, for thereby ye ſhall receive the greater judgement; for we that believe acknowledg one only in Heaven, even Chriſt:</hi> and that 2ly, which followeth in the <hi>chapter,</hi> that <hi>out of the ſame Fountain cannot proceed bitter waters and ſweet,</hi> as we <hi>find</hi> (as the <hi>Apostle</hi> doth declare) <hi>that the ſame tongue is exerciſed, as well in curſing</hi> as bleſſing, <hi>praying</hi> or <hi>preaching: my Brethren theſe things ought not ſo to be:</hi> yet then the which there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more <hi>common,</hi> as is evident <hi>among us</hi> in this place: the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing week being in <hi>London,</hi> I went, the <hi>Lord</hi> directing me, in <hi>love</hi> (ſeeing Mr.-late-Sir-<hi>Richard Bream</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter-hall</hi>) and had much ſpeech with him, he telling me of his own <hi>accord,</hi> that the <hi>people,</hi> many of them of <hi>Windſor,</hi> had brought up <hi>ſome nine Articles</hi> to ſwear and prove them againſt me; and that the firſt of them, or at leaſt one of them, was this, That I ſhould affirm, <hi>that I ſhould be one of them ſhould judg them at the laſt day;</hi> and ſhould confirm it with this Scripture, <hi>whoſe ſins
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118367:18"/>ye do remit, they are remitted,</hi> and <hi>whoſe ſins ye do retain, they are retained;</hi> the reſidue he could not tell, only he ſaid, he had <hi>rebuked</hi> them for it, and would not allow them to go on in their purpoſe by any means.</p>
               <p>The next day not looking for Maſter <hi>Kind</hi> again, he having no warrant neither heretofore, nor as yet: Yet I found him here, with his <hi>company fortified,</hi> and ready to go on as heretofore, with whom having ſome diſcourſe, after that I had told them, which in effect I had done before; ſith they would needs that Mr. <hi>Kind</hi> ſhould <hi>teach</hi> or <hi>ſpeak</hi> unto them, he having yet no <hi>authority</hi> ſo to do, I would <hi>deſcend</hi> and be willing, that he ſhould ſpeak one part of the time, in the morning, and I the reſt; and ſo again to do the ſame in <hi>love</hi> and <hi>ſubmiſſion to the Lord in the</hi> afternoon, <hi>and let the truth prevail and have dominion over both:</hi> but this they <hi>would not</hi> (I know) they <hi>dare not, cannot yeeld unto, for though the truth doth not, error doth ſeek to ſecure it ſelf in a corner, or at leaſt with ſome outward force,</hi> as <hi>the preaching</hi> and doctrine of this young man <hi>doth.</hi> This day coming into the <hi>Castle,</hi> and ſeeing the <hi>ſouldiers</hi> at the <hi>Guard,</hi> as I paſſed by, I ſaid, I think I muſt ſpeak the <hi>Word of God</hi> to you, which they <hi>readily accepted,</hi> and after a little while ſent for me, by order of the Leivtenant, to the <hi>Chappel;</hi> where I ſpake about an hour, out of the <hi>third of Luke,</hi> in the which I was much <hi>refreſhed,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in <hi>memory,</hi> of the <hi>ſouldiers readineſs to hear the Word of God</hi> at the <hi>beginning</hi> of theſe times, above <hi>other men,</hi> of whom I had occaſion to ſpeak from the <hi>Souldiers asking Iohn, And what ſhall we do?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This laſt day, coming as heretofore at the <hi>appointed</hi> time, I found the doors <hi>ſhut;</hi> our men that will <hi>needs</hi> be called <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens</hi> preſent, ſaid, the time was not <hi>yet,</hi> (but ſayd I) you render that for a <hi>cauſe,</hi> which is <hi>none,</hi> the <hi>cauſe is ſure</hi> your <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of me,</hi> which they could not <hi>deny;</hi> there were many preſent and much <hi>offended,</hi> eſpecially when I told them, that <hi>what they did,</hi> was of the ſame <hi>nature,</hi> with that which did <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram;</hi> and taking aſide Mr. <hi>Kind,</hi> told him, That what he did was not well, not <hi>only to break the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God</hi> and <hi>man (himſelf,)</hi> but even to <hi>teach men ſo to do,</hi> as indeed he doth; upholding the people in evil and ſin, both <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and his Chriſt,</hi> which they in their own <hi>Conſciences</hi> cannot deny.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:118367:19"/>
               <p> Now it is very marvellous, this <hi>evil ſpirit and power</hi> (thus to the <hi>diſhonor</hi> of God, and his <hi>most holy Spouſe or Church</hi>) ſhould finde, as they ſay, and as it ſeems it doth, ſo <hi>great encouragement</hi> and <hi>ſtrengthening,</hi> not only <hi>from hence,</hi> but alſo <hi>from elſewhere;</hi> inſomuch as they <hi>boaſt</hi> of <hi>Committees, Parliament-men,</hi> the <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of Divines,</hi> Mr. <hi>Peters,</hi> the <hi>Governor of our Caſtles ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of them,</hi> the <hi>Lord Whitlocks;</hi> yea I am <hi>confidently</hi> told by Mr. <hi>Cokayn</hi> (that I name not many others of equal, yea of greater note then he) whoſe word I ſuppoſe we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, that this <hi>whole matter, is ſupported with much endeavor, even by ſome of our neighbors at Eaton;</hi> yea I have ſome, or rather great <hi>cauſe</hi> to <hi>beleeve</hi> it, <hi>for as God is witneſs,</hi> whom I ſerve in the Spirit of him in the Goſpel of his Son, they have <hi>withstood</hi> me in the <hi>truth of God,</hi> almoſt ever ſince they <hi>came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe parts,</hi> having in manner <hi>whiſpered me,</hi> and <hi>my many lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle young and innocent babes to death, with their lyes</hi> and <hi>falſe reports, and not a few concerning me;</hi> making me <hi>guilty,</hi> and a <hi>tranſgreſſor,</hi> in the things wherein I have been found faithful <hi>to God</hi> and <hi>men:</hi> This I <hi>ſpeak as of neceſſity, the truth of God,</hi> for the <hi>vindication of it ſelf</hi> in <hi>me, forcing me ſo to do;</hi> that I may ſay, as <hi>Craeſus ſon did,</hi> that never ſpoke <hi>before, What, kill my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther! kill and crucifie my Saviour, yea the Saviour of the Land!</hi> which I am <hi>ſure</hi> they <hi>have done in me;</hi> they that <hi>beleeve not, may come and ſee, as Thomas did,</hi> and <hi>thruſt their hands into the wounds made in his ſides, for he bleedeth even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh among us,</hi> as it is ſaid, <hi>they crucified the ſon of God afreſh unto themſelves.</hi> This laſt Sabboth, the Governor came him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into the Caſtle, otherwiſe peradventure I might have had opportunity to have ſpoken to the people, and the ſouldiers, as before in the Caſtle; but I ſhall conclude with this wiſh, <hi>God have mercy on the power of the Nation,</hi> that they <hi>may not ſuffer any power of theirs,</hi> much leſs any <hi>earthly power oppoſed to theirs,</hi> to <hi>oppoſe it ſelf</hi> againſt the <hi>power of God</hi> and his anointed <hi>One our Saviour, Amen, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Quae <hi>tua</hi> ſunt <hi>facias,</hi> quae <hi>functio</hi> una <hi>requirit</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Comittas ſoli,</hi> Caetera <hi>cuncta Deo.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thy</hi> duty do, <hi>and Calling</hi> juſt fulfil</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In both thee ſafe keep,</hi> Jah, Jehovah <hi>will.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="postscript">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:118367:19"/>
            <head>The firſt Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>BEing a Tranſcript of certain <hi>Letters,</hi> with a double <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation</hi> made and annexed, for a further <hi>light</hi> to this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and mine own <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>true intent</hi> in it.</p>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter by way of Petition to the <hi>Councel</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> occaſioned, as it doth declare.</head>
               <head type="sub">To the Right <hi>Honourable</hi> the preſent <hi>Councel</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> by Authority of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>HAving this laſt night had intelligence by a</hi> worthy <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of this</hi> Councel <hi>of an</hi> information <hi>and</hi> complaint <hi>made againſt me by</hi> Col. Whitchcot, <hi>the preſent Governor of</hi> Windſor <hi>Caſtle, I humbly</hi> beg <hi>to repreſent before you, that I have been in a conſtant way of</hi> ſuffering wrong <hi>from the ſaid</hi> Governour (<hi>at leaſt from him as an</hi> Inſtrument) <hi>as many of</hi> great note, <hi>and ſome</hi> deſerving <hi>Members of this</hi> Councel <hi>can I am ſure</hi> atteſt) <hi>even ever ſince immediately</hi> before <hi>the</hi> Armies <hi>laſt march to</hi> London, <hi>for the</hi> eſtabliſhment <hi>of the</hi> preſent power <hi>as now it is, which I pray</hi> God <hi>to continue in</hi> Righteouſneſs <hi>and</hi> Peace, <hi>for the</hi> quiet <hi>and</hi> Profit <hi>of the</hi> Common-wealth; <hi>but as</hi> becomes <hi>my Profeſſion, I have with</hi> patience <hi>and</hi> ſilence <hi>as to</hi> men, <hi>born the</hi> reproach, <hi>and ſuffered the</hi> wrong, crying yet in my heart to God the moſt righteous judg of all men and actions, to bring forth my righteouſneſs, even in the Conſcience of mine accuſer, <hi>and</hi> this Nation, <hi>which</hi> I am confident <hi>he will now do</hi> before you, <hi>he having given the occaſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherefore I moſt humbly</hi> implore <hi>the</hi> Almighty God, <hi>whoſe</hi> preſence <hi>is with you, that according to the</hi> wiſdom given you from above, <hi>you may</hi> go down <hi>after</hi> his example <hi>into a narrow</hi> view, <hi>and</hi> ſearch <hi>after the</hi> nature <hi>and</hi> ground <hi>of this</hi> complaint, for the like hath not <hi>yet</hi> come before you, <hi>that it may be as a</hi> ſign <hi>to the</hi> Nation, <hi>which I heartily wiſh in the</hi> firſt year <hi>of your</hi> Commiſſion, <hi>that there is in you of that</hi> wiſdom of God <hi>was ſometimes in</hi> Solomon, <hi>the firſt year of his</hi> Reign, <hi>to that</hi> intent <hi>and</hi> purpoſe, <hi>that as he</hi> was to that, <hi>you may appear to be deſign'd</hi> of God <hi>(by righteous judgment) to give to</hi> this Nation reſt <hi>in</hi> Righteouſneſs, Peace <hi>and</hi> Plenty, <hi>ſo prays</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Petitioner to <hi>God</hi> for you. <hi>ROBERT BACON.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:118367:20"/>
               <head>A Letter to the Lievtenant General, now his Excellency the Lord <hi>General Cromwel</hi> (whoſe <hi>favour</hi> I humbly <hi>beg</hi> in the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication</hi> of it, being nothing at all to his <hi>diſhonour</hi>) occaſioned as the Contents do declare.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe</hi> light <hi>of the</hi> Lord <hi>be your</hi> guide, <hi>to</hi> lead <hi>you into thoſe</hi> ways <hi>that</hi> conduce <hi>to his</hi> glory, <hi>the</hi> Kingdoms good, <hi>and your own</hi> internal-eternal peace <hi>and</hi> reſt <hi>in</hi> Chriſt, Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The last night, being</hi> April 30. <hi>the two late</hi> Captains <hi>of this</hi> Caſtle, Robinſon <hi>and</hi> Beale, <hi>came and repreſented to me the ground of their</hi> remove <hi>hence, as</hi> your ſelf <hi>(they ſay)</hi> declared <hi>it. Now becauſe I am alſo under the</hi> ſame, <hi>or a greater</hi> charge, <hi>as they</hi> report, <hi>I undertake with your</hi> leave <hi>and their</hi> requeſt <hi>to lay the</hi> matter <hi>of my</hi> accuſation, <hi>and my own</hi> clearing <hi>of my ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you,</hi> though the Lord will clear me; <hi>that is,</hi> his own truth and image in me: <hi>for</hi> nothing elſe do I deſire to vindicate, the innocency of which muſt and will appear: <hi>there be two par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, I underſtand, in order to the late remove</hi> charged <hi>on me, I think he mentioned Mr.</hi> Lockier <hi>was the man poſſest you with it; The firſt was mine adhering to the</hi> Parliament-men priſoners <hi>here. The ſecond my</hi> provoking <hi>the</hi> Souldiers <hi>to take the Castle</hi> for them. <hi>Sir, I am not in the leaſt meaſure, through the</hi> grace <hi>of</hi> God, <hi>ſo much as inclining to any ſuch</hi> thing, <hi>but do altogether</hi> abominate <hi>the endeavour both of the</hi> one <hi>and the</hi> other. <hi>The</hi> Lord <hi>is</hi> witneſs <hi>how I</hi> ſuffered, <hi>and was</hi> oppreſſed <hi>by the</hi> late Presbyterian power <hi>ſo called, which</hi> yoak <hi>was by you, as a</hi> princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal inſtrument <hi>in the hand</hi> of God, <hi>broken in</hi> peeces, <hi>I ſuppoſe to the</hi> joy <hi>of all</hi> good men. <hi>And therefore I cannot be in</hi> reaſon thought <hi>to</hi> promote <hi>that which indeed I waited</hi> upon God to remove: <hi>concerning the</hi> perſons <hi>of thoſe</hi> priſoners <hi>I never had ſpeech</hi> with them <hi>but</hi> once, <hi>and that was not for above half a quarter of an hour, meeting them in the yard: Cancerning the provoking of the</hi> Souldiery <hi>to any kind of</hi> deſign whatſoever, <hi>it is to me a very great</hi> marvel, <hi>there ſhould be any ſuch</hi> ſuggeſtions; <hi>but</hi> that this is not ſtrange to me, <hi>what our</hi> Saviour <hi>ſays,</hi> they ſhall ſpeak all manner of evil againſt you falſly, for my names ſake: <hi>this hath been my</hi> lot <hi>from the</hi> Biſhops, Presbyters, <hi>and now</hi> laſt <hi>beyond all</hi> thought <hi>by ſome of</hi> them commonly <hi>caſt'd</hi> Independents. <hi>There are of your own</hi> Family, <hi>I ſuppoſe, can give ſome</hi> teſtimony <hi>concerning me;</hi> but I ſeek not the teſtimony of men, God will witneſs for me, as he is witneſs in me; that as in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118367:20"/>the fear of God, with all good Conſcience both towards him and men, I have behav'd my ſelf in this place, ſeeking by all means in publique and in private to advance the teſtimony of the coming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in faith and love, waiting for the effect and fruit of it in peace. <hi>Truly Sir, I have prayed unto the</hi> Lord, <hi>and to that</hi> I preſs, <hi>that there might be no more</hi> war in the Land, <hi>and therefore</hi> would <hi>that every man (I would be an</hi> example therein, <hi>as well as a</hi> Preacher thereof <hi>to others) would begin to</hi> war againſt himſelf, <hi>which I am</hi> ſure <hi>would make the</hi> other war <hi>ſoon to</hi> ceaſe. <hi>You have it</hi> likewiſe <hi>(they ſay) and not only upon</hi> report, <hi>for</hi> your ſelf (<hi>they</hi> ſay, <hi>you</hi> ſay) <hi>have been a</hi> hearer of me, <hi>that I</hi> ſeem to deny all Ordinances, <hi>yea they ſay the</hi> very Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. <hi>Truly Sir, it is not what you</hi> ſay, <hi>or what others</hi> report, <hi>but what is, that I muſt have</hi> eſtabliſhment in. <hi>By the</hi> Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>I underſtand the</hi> Commands of God, <hi>that</hi> concern my ſelf, <hi>which whiles in his</hi> power <hi>I</hi> ſubmit to; <hi>I</hi> judg my ſelf one of them through grace that keeps the Ordinances of God: <hi>But it may be</hi> ſome <hi>call their own</hi> inventions <hi>and</hi> Idolls <hi>by that</hi> name, <hi>as you know the</hi> Jews <hi>did; And ſuch like</hi> Phariſees <hi>there</hi> be now not a few: <hi>But that I may be</hi> calumniated <hi>to ſome</hi> purpoſe, 'tis <hi>ſaid, I deny the</hi> Scriptures. <hi>Truly Sir, there be many in</hi> words confeſs them, but in life and deed deny them: <hi>I find of thoſe, that will</hi> needs be offended with me, <hi>even whether I</hi> will <hi>or</hi> no, <hi>that</hi> ſay <hi>the</hi> Scriptures <hi>are the</hi> word of God; <hi>but I bleſs</hi> God <hi>I</hi> know <hi>them to be</hi> ſo, <hi>becauſe I find the</hi> effect <hi>and</hi> tenor <hi>of</hi> them <hi>in</hi> my ſelf. <hi>And I am</hi> confident <hi>others</hi> find <hi>and</hi> feel <hi>the ſame in</hi> my word, life <hi>and</hi> Converſation, <hi>and therefore are offended with</hi> me, <hi>as thoſe of the</hi> like ſpirit <hi>have been</hi> heretofore. <hi>Sir, how I have in my heart prayed to</hi> God for you, <hi>is</hi> ſecret alone to him before whom all is open. <hi>Yea</hi> what joy I have had in you, <hi>he</hi> only knows; <hi>but</hi> now <hi>I</hi> fear, <hi>I</hi> fear, I fear, <hi>you are like to be, if not</hi> alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, enſnared of the world <hi>and</hi> men. <hi>Our Saviour</hi> ſays, beware of men: <hi>Your</hi> name, power <hi>and</hi> proweſs <hi>have drawn all</hi> mens eyes upon you; ſome, <hi>and ſurely of</hi> that Company you <hi>will find the</hi> moſt, <hi>will not only</hi> act <hi>as you would have</hi> them, (<hi>to get your</hi> favour, <hi>and thereby</hi> honour <hi>and</hi> wealth;) <hi>but over-act</hi> your will <hi>and</hi> Commands <hi>to your</hi> prejudice <hi>and</hi> diſhonour: <hi>this</hi> upon my life will be the effect of the late complaint from <hi>Windſor,</hi> if you countenance or connive at it. <hi>There be</hi> others <hi>have their</hi> eyes <hi>and</hi> hearts too, <hi>towards</hi> you; <hi>but it is in the way of</hi> pitying of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118367:21"/>you,
<note place="margin">I have always <hi>thought</hi> men in <hi>high place</hi> (ſith <hi>high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> are <hi>ſlippery places</hi>) have more <hi>need</hi> of <hi>pity</hi> and <hi>prayer</hi> then <hi>applauſe.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and</hi> praying <hi>for you, being forc't to ſtand aloof from</hi> you <hi>though the</hi> reproaches caſt on them, <hi>and the</hi> prejudices had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, <hi>of which</hi> ſort of men, <hi>I could name not</hi> a few, whoſe counſel would be (<hi>I ſpeak</hi> what <hi>I</hi> know) <hi>the</hi> Councel of God to you. <hi>Sir, I beſeech you, do not think</hi> therefore <hi>all is</hi> well <hi>with</hi> you, <hi>becauſe</hi> all <hi>about</hi> you applaud your ſayings <hi>and</hi> doings; <hi>many</hi> mighty Emperors <hi>and</hi> potent Kings, <hi>have</hi> been undone this way.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I could name a</hi> third ſort <hi>of</hi> men, <hi>that look upon you only with an</hi> eye of envy: <hi>againſt this kind of</hi> enchantment, <hi>an</hi> evil eye, <hi>there's no better</hi> antidote, <hi>then the</hi> true fear and knowledg of God, <hi>(i.e.) a</hi> union with him, <hi>againſt</hi> whom <hi>all</hi> conteſts muſt needs be in vain. <hi>Sir, Theſe things I have written</hi> as to the Lord, <hi>to whom not in all things to</hi> approve my ſelf, <hi>I know no</hi> greater <hi>or</hi> worſer death: <hi>I</hi> live not, <hi>unleſs</hi> the Lord live in me, <hi>whereby I become</hi> his, and</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your ſervant, for</hi> his Sons ſake <hi>Rob. Bacon.</hi>
                  </signed> 
                  <dateline>Windſor Caſtle <date>May 1. 1649.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>Poſcript, If you neglect to <hi>clear us,</hi> and give a right judgment in the <hi>thing,</hi> God himſelf will <hi>do it,</hi> and our <hi>reproachers ſhall be aſhamed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter to the <hi>Governor,</hi> after that he had threatned me, firſt to <hi>depart the Caſtle,</hi> ſecondly that he would <hi>ſhut the Church doors</hi> againſt me, as indeed, he afterwards did.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Honorable Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I <hi>would not</hi> offend <hi>any man, much leſs</hi> you, leaſt of all <hi>the</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent power <hi>and</hi> authority <hi>of the</hi> Nation, <hi>yet you are</hi> offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>with me, and go about to</hi> ſuſpect <hi>me, and to</hi> deal <hi>with me as an</hi> enemy, <hi>not only unto</hi> you, <hi>but to the</hi> Nation; <hi>And ſo</hi> by you, <hi>am I put into this</hi> condition, <hi>not to be in</hi> expectation <hi>of any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> likelihood <hi>of</hi> ſubſiſtance <hi>in the</hi> Land; <hi>The Lord</hi> forgive you this wrong you do me, <hi>and my whole</hi> enlarged <hi>family; but this I am</hi> prepared <hi>through the</hi> grace of God <hi>to</hi> ſuſtain, <hi>and much
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118367:21"/>more, even to</hi> death <hi>and</hi> bonds <hi>for the</hi> Goſpel ſake; <hi>for which I am under ſo great</hi> contempt with you: <hi>If I have offended you upon</hi> any other <hi>account, why do you not</hi> deal <hi>with me</hi> according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? <hi>but it ſeems nothing</hi> troubles you, <hi>but my</hi> preaching <hi>and</hi> teſtimony, <hi>which yet is not</hi> mine, <hi>but the</hi> teſtimony of Chriſt himſelf. <hi>And therefore on that behalf I am</hi> exceeding glad; <hi>for ſo</hi> perſecuted <hi>they the</hi> Apoſtles <hi>and</hi> Prophets <hi>that were of</hi> old. <hi>Sir, I</hi> adjure <hi>you before the</hi> living God, <hi>and</hi> thoſe that promote the ſame thing with you, before whom you ſhall be accountable within a very little while, <hi>whether this</hi> Engagement <hi>and</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour <hi>againſt me be not rather to</hi> fulfil your will, <hi>and</hi> ſatisfie your luſt, <hi>then for to</hi> pleaſe <hi>and ſerve the</hi> State thereby. <hi>That it to the</hi> former, <hi>and not the</hi> latter, <hi>will be made apparent to every</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <hi>wiſe</hi> Chriſtian <hi>man, and that thus you are doing</hi> nothing now, <hi>but what you with</hi> others <hi>have been</hi> endeavouring <hi>ever ſince before the</hi> Armies <hi>laſt march to</hi> London; <hi>and that by</hi> ſundry means <hi>and</hi> ways, <hi>as will be made</hi> evident; <hi>ſo that this is but</hi> idem agere, <hi>hoping you have an</hi> opportunity <hi>to effect</hi> that now, <hi>which you ſought then, though upon other</hi> grounds: <hi>But as for the</hi> latter, <hi>it cannot be; for</hi> God is witneſs againſt you, <hi>and</hi> will be witneſs to them, the preſent power, <hi>as</hi> he <hi>is</hi> in me, <hi>that you do them</hi> great diſ-ſervice; <hi>for what do you elſe</hi> hereby, <hi>but make them, as much as in you is, like</hi> your ſelf, offenders with that which is good? <hi>ſo that you</hi> debaſe, <hi>and as much as in you is,</hi> hinder what they profeſs to promote, the free and open preaching of the Goſpel; <hi>and</hi> no other Goſpel <hi>is</hi> there, <hi>or can be</hi> preacht, <hi>then that which</hi> is, <hi>and hath</hi> been <hi>by me,</hi> unworthy in this place: <hi>this I ſpeak, as not</hi> prejudicing thoſe <hi>that give out the</hi> ſame teſtimony <hi>with me;</hi> for the way of life and peace is but one, one Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir, as being in a great</hi> ſtraite <hi>betwixt</hi> God <hi>and</hi> mine own heart <hi>in order to your</hi> Command, <hi>which is as to</hi> acceptance <hi>of the world a</hi> preſent ſnare <hi>upon me, I would be</hi> ſatisfied <hi>by ſome</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony <hi>of</hi> Scripture, <hi>as a</hi> Caſe of Conſcience <hi>by</hi> Mr. Simonds, <hi>or</hi> Mr. Batchiler, <hi>or any</hi> other, whether in this point I can be any ways warranted to ſit in ſilence to morrow, notwithſtanding your Command. <hi>And that for theſe</hi> cauſes; <hi>firſt, for that I</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie no other <hi>thing, then that which did the</hi> Prophets and Apoſtles, <hi>and</hi> Chriſt himſelf; <hi>If I do, or have done</hi> otherwiſe, <hi>let it be made to appear by the</hi> oppoſers <hi>and</hi> deniers <hi>of</hi> it. <hi>Secondly, as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118367:22"/>for this</hi> publick place <hi>and</hi> liberty, <hi>with all</hi> thankfulneſs <hi>I</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>I have for it the</hi> preſent Authority <hi>of the</hi> Nation, <hi>as you know, and did</hi> your ſelf conſent to, and promote, <hi>and they have not as I know</hi> revok'd <hi>the ſame; whether</hi> your will, <hi>or</hi> their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>ought, by me to be</hi> bowed down to, <hi>I have</hi> conſulted with God <hi>in mine</hi> own heart, <hi>and the</hi> teſtimony <hi>of the</hi> Scripture, <hi>and the</hi> practiſe of believing men, <hi>that in</hi> obedience to God, <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially having too for it,</hi> the Authority of men uncontradicted, <hi>ſaving by your</hi> only word, <hi>I find my ſelf</hi> neceſſitated, <hi>though in the midſt of</hi> many temptations <hi>as to the</hi> outward man, <hi>to go on as in</hi> times paſt <hi>in</hi> publick, <hi>unleſs I am</hi> hindred <hi>by your</hi> outward force: <hi>to which I ſhall</hi> willingly yield my ſelf a Captive <hi>in</hi> this caſe, <hi>even</hi> one <hi>in</hi> bonds <hi>for</hi> the Goſpel. <hi>In which</hi> Captivity <hi>I ſhall have more</hi> freedom <hi>then mine</hi> oppoſers. <hi>Sir,</hi> hearken to the ſecret word of God in your heart; <hi>And be</hi> not offended with him, as you are cauſleſly, <hi>who is, Sir,</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>A true <hi>Lover</hi> and <hi>Servant</hi> of <hi>you,</hi> but in <hi>the Lord,</hi> ROBERT BACON.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>This Letter was pen'd (I ſuppoſe by Mr. <hi>Bachiler,</hi>) and ſent by Mr. <hi>Mills</hi> in the name of the Town to Mr. <hi>Holland.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>WIth all reſpects and thankfulneſs returned you for that</hi> great <hi>care and</hi> unwearied pains taken for us in that which is (and ſhould be) <hi>the</hi> chiefeſt means of our happineſs, the planting of the preaching of the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt amongſt us, <hi>and your procuring for us towards it</hi> 50 l. per annum <hi>from the Committee of plundred Miniſters, out of the Dean and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons Lands of</hi> Windſor, <hi>in this Borough of new</hi> Windſor: <hi>we further imbolden our ſelves upon you the</hi> only Inſtrument, whom God in his good providence hath preſerved to forward ſo glorious a work; <hi>And do give you a ſhort account of our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours and proceedings therein: we had an eye upon Mr.</hi> Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds <hi>of</hi> Holland, <hi>and made it our buſineſs to have brought him to this place; but God hath otherwiſe ordered, firſt him, and then our ſelves.</hi> Providence, after our longing deſires to ſettle
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118367:22"/>this work of the Goſpel in this Town of <hi>Windſor,</hi> hath ordered, that Mr. <hi>Robert Bacon,</hi> Maſter of Arts, coming to ſupply the
<note n="*" place="margin">Being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of him to that intent <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited</hi> there.</note> room of Mr. <hi>Bachiler in the Caſtle,</hi> where he being well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of, and well known; <hi>ſome ten days paſt</hi> we made our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires known unto him, to preach alſo in the Town this laſt Lords day: ſo that not only that good report we have had of him, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that experience we now have of his ſound Orthodox judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>in</hi> the truth of Jeſus Chriſt, preached unto us, confirmeth us of his ability and worth; ſo that <hi>we meeting together upon the debate of the whole buſineſs,</hi> he is made choice to be (nemine contradicente) the Miniſter to preach in the Pariſh-Church twice every week, <hi>viz. once on the Lords day</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">There being then a <hi>Vicar</hi> in being.</note> 
                  <hi>and once in the week-days, and hope to raiſe this</hi> 50 l. you have ſo honourably procured for the work to
<note n="*" place="margin">The fifth part yet, I ſcarce ever had there, in any ſuch way.</note> 50 l. more, by our voluntary ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>Therefore we requeſt you further, to perfect this work for us, and to preſent him to the Committee of plundred Miniſters, that they may accordingly appoint him to be the perſon to offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate in this Pariſh-Church, according to their Order of the</hi> 23. <hi>of Jan. laſt; and that alſo you will be pleaſed to obtain for us the continuance of the yearly payment of</hi> 50 l. <hi>from the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee; for which and all</hi> your faithful and continued care and reſpects of us in the ſaving of ſouls, the Lord multiply bleſſings upon you, <hi>which are the earneſt deſires and prayers of,</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute> 
                  <signed>Your very thankful loving friends to ſerve you,
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Chriſtopher Whitchcot.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Charles Burges,</hi> Mayor.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Spenſer.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Math: Day.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Rob. Bennet.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>George Starkey.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Baker.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Redding.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>William Botterel.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Will: Mills.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Will: Church.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Andrew Plumpton.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Chapman.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Windſor Caſtle</hi> 
                     <date>the 13. <hi>of April,</hi> 1647.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>The Copy of the Order of the Committee, we have ſent you now by Mr. <hi>Mills,</hi> who is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to wait upon you, concerning the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="protestation">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:118367:23"/>
               <head>The first Protestation.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>An humble and true <hi>Teſtimony</hi> or <hi>Proteſtation</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>manner</hi> and <hi>end</hi> of my <hi>Converſation,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Octob 7th. 1649.</note> (as elſe-where) ſo ſince I came to <hi>Windſor,</hi> which I was <hi>neceſsitated</hi> to give, and read this day in the Congregation, for the <hi>ſilencing</hi> (if it may be) of the <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>minds</hi> of all that <hi>conceive evil of me.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>HAving been</hi> converſant <hi>the ſpace of two years, or thereabouts at</hi> Windſor, <hi>by the</hi> Authority <hi>of</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, <hi>and the</hi> importunity <hi>and</hi> deſire <hi>of many of the chief of the Inhabitants of that place, as the</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour <hi>Col. Whitchcot,</hi> the Mayor <hi>that then was, Mr.</hi> Day <hi>a Juſtice of Peace for the Town, Sir Robert Bennet</hi> ſince dead, <hi>Mr. Mills, Mr. Cleaver ſince dead, Mr.</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiler, Chaplain <hi>then to the</hi> Gariſon, <hi>Mr.</hi> Beake, <hi>Dr.</hi> Spenſer, <hi>Mr.</hi> Redding <hi>and others.</hi> I have all this while (as God ſhall bear me witneſs at the great day of his appearing) minded, deſigned, proſecuted, ſought <hi>to</hi> magnifie, <hi>and</hi> bring forth, <hi>into the</hi> hearts, lives, <hi>and</hi> Converſations <hi>of all</hi> ſorts <hi>and Sexes</hi> of <hi>perſons,</hi> no other matter <hi>or</hi> thing whatſoever, <hi>then the</hi> pure <hi>and</hi> naked teſtimony <hi>of the</hi> coming <hi>of</hi> our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>for the</hi> Reconciliation <hi>of</hi> men <hi>to</hi> God, <hi>and</hi> one <hi>to</hi> another <hi>in</hi> him, <hi>that there</hi> might be peace on earth, <hi>as there is</hi> good will <hi>in</hi> God, <hi>and thoſe that are</hi> born of him, <hi>to</hi> men. <hi>Neither do</hi> I know, <hi>or</hi> ſhall <hi>hereafter through the</hi> Grace <hi>of</hi> God, deſign, <hi>or</hi> purſue, <hi>any</hi> other <hi>thing.</hi> So help me God.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>ROBERT BACON.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="protestation">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:118367:23"/>
               <argument>
                  <p>A ſecond <hi>Proteſtation</hi> made in <hi>ſecret</hi> before the <hi>Lord,</hi> and put thereupon in <hi>writing,</hi> and now <hi>publiſhed,</hi> as much as in <hi>me is,</hi> for a <hi>remora,</hi> or <hi>let</hi> to the <hi>flowing in of evil</hi> in the Land, that I, and as many as <hi>the Lord our God ſhall call,</hi> may not be <hi>overtaken,</hi> or <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwhelm'd</hi> therewith; in the <hi>which,</hi> doubtleſs <hi>there be</hi> to whom <hi>this</hi> ſhall <hi>come,</hi> will with the like <hi>readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and upon the <hi>like ground</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">I mean, <hi>vow to God and keep it;</hi> for there be a <hi>people,</hi> that are <hi>able</hi> ſo to <hi>do.</hi>
                     </note> do, and <hi>ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> have done.</p>
               </argument>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Gather my <hi>Saints</hi> together <hi>unto me, thoſe</hi> that have made a <hi>Covenant</hi> with <hi>me</hi> by <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> 
                     <bibl>Pſal. 50.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>I Do hereby <hi>promiſe</hi> and <hi>proteſt,</hi> that by the <hi>help of God Almighty,</hi> and the <hi>obedience</hi> and <hi>grace</hi> of his <hi>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Son, revealed in me</hi> in ſome <hi>meaſure,</hi> through his moſt <hi>holy Spirit</hi> of <hi>light, life,</hi> and <hi>love,</hi> in <hi>all</hi> things <hi>uprightly</hi> to <hi>demean my ſelf,</hi> both <hi>towards God, inwardly revealed in me;</hi> and <hi>man, outwardly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing</hi> unto <hi>me;</hi> according to the moſt <hi>holy Law,</hi> and <hi>will</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> as it hath <hi>been,</hi> and <hi>is witneſſed</hi> unto, by the <hi>Scriptures</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> by <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles, and the <hi>remnant</hi> of the <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> that are <hi>till now,</hi> the <hi>bleſsing</hi> of all <hi>Generations:</hi> To this of a <hi>ready mind,</hi> in the <hi>hope</hi> of <hi>eternal life</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> I <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> my <hi>name,</hi> together with the <hi>reſt</hi> of thoſe are <hi>made willing</hi> in this <hi>day</hi> of <hi>Gods Grace</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>ROBERT BACON.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="postscript">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:118367:24"/>
            <p>The ſecond Poſtſcript, touching a report with <hi>great confidence</hi> given out by one of our now <hi>Neighbours</hi> at <hi>Eaton,</hi> not any of the <hi>fellows,</hi> but <hi>one</hi> whoſe <hi>abiding</hi> is there among them; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>whom</hi> I will only ſay this, that he being a <hi>Companion,</hi> and a daily <hi>guest there,</hi> as well as their <hi>Tenant;</hi> yea, not only a <hi>fellow-Member,</hi> but of late, in the great City an <hi>Elder</hi> of a <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect Church and Congregation:</hi> it hath been to me of a <hi>very ſad</hi> and <hi>lamentable import,</hi> that after all theſe <hi>pretences,</hi> no better <hi>fruit</hi> then the <hi>cauſleſs and moſt unjuſt reproach of his Neighbor, againſt the mind of the whole Law of God, ſhould be yielded of ſo eminent a plant</hi> as <hi>he would ſeem to be:</hi> truly it minded me of the <hi>Text</hi> I of late heard the new <hi>conduct on, there, Cut it down, why cumbreth it the ground?</hi> for certainly the ground that bringeth forth <hi>nought,</hi> as <hi>ſaith the Apoſtle,</hi> but <hi>Bryars</hi> and <hi>Thorns,</hi> is <hi>near unto curſing,</hi> yea it is <hi>even curſed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Gentleman hath had ſome 3. or 4. particular things of <hi>offence</hi> to <hi>charge</hi> me with, which he did not at all in <hi>private</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen unto me, according to a <hi>Rule</hi> they pretend to demean them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in things of this <hi>Nature by,</hi> but in the <hi>preſence</hi> of <hi>divers,</hi> eſpecially one whom he knew had ſome <hi>reſpect</hi> unto <hi>me;</hi> for which he ſeems to be not alittle <hi>offended, upbraiding him of it, as an evil ſcarce to be allowed,</hi> rendring for his reaſon in general, <hi>his countenancing</hi> not <hi>only here, but appearing openly in</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, on <hi>the behalf of one, that though he ſeemed (ſaid he) to walk according to rule, yet he is indeed a very great ſeducer, and a marvellous let to all good in this place:</hi> which when he underſtood to be ſpoken of me, and that with great heat, he told him that he ſhould take time to <hi>conſider</hi> of it, but could not for the preſent give <hi>credit</hi> to it, unleſs he ſhould <hi>underſtand more</hi> then ever he could <hi>believe</hi> concerning me <hi>hitherto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt was this, That I ſhould borrow <hi>Col. Okeys Horſe</hi> ſometimes, and when I had it in my <hi>Cuſtody,</hi> ſhould go with it into <hi>Smithfield,</hi> to <hi>ſell</hi> it <hi>there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond was this, That I ſhould be <hi>preſent</hi> where I ſaw a <hi>man</hi> in <hi>bed</hi> with another mans Wife.</p>
            <p>The third, That Mrs. <hi>Ceenee</hi> ſometimes <hi>lodged</hi> at my houſe.</p>
            <p>The fourth and the laſt, that no man can tell that hears me, whether I will ſpeak from, or of <hi>God,</hi> or the <hi>Devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe were named of him with this profeſſion, that he
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118367:24"/>would make proof of them, telling it him, as glad to have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of this nature to report of me.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Now as touching <hi>Col. Okey,</hi> I ſcarce ever had any ſpeech with him, ſave only once, he ſpoke to me at <hi>Slow</hi> going to meet the Lord General coming out of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As concerning his <hi>Horſe, I</hi> never borrowed any of him, <hi>he</hi> and the <hi>Lord knows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Yet I will not deny, but being in <hi>Glocester,</hi> I came to <hi>London</hi> upon a <hi>Horſe</hi> which <hi>Colonel Okeys Wife</hi> ſaid was <hi>hers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. This Horſe <hi>Col. Maſſie,</hi> now <hi>priſoner</hi> in the <hi>Tower,</hi> when he ſeized on me with ſome 16. of his Troop, ordered for my uſe in this <hi>Journey,</hi> which as I <hi>did not,</hi> ſo I had no <hi>cauſe</hi> to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, whoſe it <hi>was,</hi> being his <hi>priſoner,</hi> and ſo <hi>wholly</hi> in this <hi>bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs paſſive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. This Horſe <hi>trotting</hi> altogether, I road not on till I came to <hi>Warwick,</hi> being till then in the cuſtody of the <hi>Corporal,</hi> and one <hi>Trooper, two moſt honeſt and Chriſtian men,</hi> riding till then on the Corporalls Horſe, and he riding on that appointed for me, both which did of their <hi>own minds offer</hi> and <hi>endeavour</hi> to <hi>exchange</hi> it <hi>for me,</hi> that I might have one more <hi>eaſie,</hi> nothing ſuſpecting, but that it had been the Governours <hi>own,</hi> who had done me all this wrong, which ten Horſes could not give me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Col. Maſſie</hi> did himſelf before the <hi>Committee,</hi> promiſe to <hi>accommodate</hi> me <hi>well,</hi> and with a good Horſe, to <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. This <hi>Horſe,</hi> as I have heard, as well as <hi>theſe men,</hi> were the <hi>States;</hi> for <hi>whom,</hi> and in whoſe <hi>cauſe,</hi> I had ſuffered great <hi>loſs</hi> before at <hi>Briſtol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. This matter is fully enough ſpoken to in a <hi>Book</hi> I writ of that relation of my <hi>ſufferings,</hi> &amp; wrong I ſuſtained in that <hi>place,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bachiler</hi> giving a ready, and full <hi>approbation</hi> of it, being the then <hi>Licenſer of Books.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. When this Book and ſuffering was, I was then juſtified of the <hi>Independents</hi> (ſo call'd) as an <hi>Independent;</hi> but many of them have ſeen cauſe to do ſince, more <hi>unwarrantably,</hi> what they then condemned the <hi>Presbyter</hi> for, whence it is my <hi>lot</hi> to <hi>ſuffer</hi> under <hi>ſome of them,</hi> as I did of <hi>their Fathers</hi> that <hi>went before;</hi> I mean thoſe, whether <hi>Prelatical,</hi> or <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> of <hi>like ſpirit</hi> with them.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:118367:25"/> 10. This Horſe I refuſed in <hi>London</hi> to <hi>deliver</hi> at the firſt challenge to Mrs. <hi>Okey,</hi> as I had cauſe to do; neither did I deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it, ſhe being a ſtranger to me, till I had an Order from the <hi>Captain-Lievtenant</hi> under <hi>Col. Maſſey</hi> ſo to do: which when I <hi>ſaw,</hi> ſhe had her <hi>Horſe,</hi> as ſhe deſired.</p>
            <p n="11">11. This Charge was in particular once alſo brought againſt me by my loving <hi>Neighbor</hi> Mr. <hi>Bachiler,</hi> who had himſelf ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified me, and the thing, in the book he <hi>licenſed;</hi> but indeed I was then <hi>related</hi> to my Honoured <hi>Lord Say,</hi> and he a <hi>man</hi> then of <hi>great power,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bachiler</hi> was not yet <hi>fellow of Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> nor had as yet by a <hi>full Table</hi> left off, <hi>truſting in God;</hi> for from his <hi>own mouth</hi> it came, (as God is witneſs, I was told by the <hi>Governor,</hi> in the <hi>preſence</hi> of his <hi>Wife,</hi> and <hi>ſome others</hi>) that he <hi>had truſted in God ſo long, that he was once like to be ſtarved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. I bleſs <hi>God through</hi> his <hi>grace</hi> I am <hi>innocent,</hi> and <hi>without</hi> blame, <hi>in my heart and life,</hi> as <hi>touching this buſineſs,</hi> both as <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and man.</hi> I do confeſs I have thought of ſome <hi>further recompence</hi> for this my <hi>ſuffering and wrong at Gloceſter,</hi> which hath been ſo judged <hi>heretofore,</hi> eſpecially of Mr. <hi>Bachiler,</hi> and thoſe of the <hi>Independant</hi> way: that I ſay not of the <hi>whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as it is now; but as ſure as God is, this adulterous and wicked Generation, having through Apoſtacy from God and his people, enriched themſelves by the ſpoils of others, care not what become of the Iſrael of God, ſo they may ſit in quiet, feeding themſelves full with the Onyons and Garlick,</hi> and <hi>other the fleſh-pots of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, let it be <hi>judged</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>man,</hi> what ſpirit this is that thus <hi>boldly,</hi> and with a <hi>moſt impudent face, reproacheth</hi> the <hi>truth</hi> of <hi>God, manifeſted in the extream ſufferings</hi> of <hi>his Saints and people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Wood,</hi> for I will not refuſe now to name him, his ſecond charge is, That I ſhould be preſent where there was a man in bed with another mans Wife.</p>
            <p>To this I will ſay, firſt in general, that where the <hi>good man ſoweth</hi> as becometh him <hi>good ſeed,</hi> there cometh <hi>the Enemy</hi> and ſoweth <hi>tares:</hi> That which I have <hi>innocently,</hi> and for the <hi>furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the truth</hi> as it is in <hi>God,</hi> declared, <hi>That this adverſary of God and me</hi> hath ſomewhere <hi>picked</hi> up to <hi>fling</hi> as <hi>dirt into my face:</hi> wherefore, as <hi>the Lord</hi> is <hi>witneſs in me,</hi> I will return it
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:118367:25"/>back from whence it came, and give out the report truly with the <hi>foundation</hi> of it, whence it hath and doth ariſe.</p>
            <p>It's not unknown to ſome, that being to ſee a Brother ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in <hi>Wells;</hi> when I came, his Wife, my Wives Siſter, told me, he was then a priſoner at <hi>Taunton,</hi> by the means of Mr. <hi>Pine,</hi> which indeed I think coſt him his life, though he was put forth again, and nothing layd to his charge; which freedom I obtained by a Letter from the L. <hi>Fairfax,</hi> that then was <hi>General:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Siſter rode behind me to <hi>Taunton,</hi> but ſhe had ordered it to take Horſe at one <hi>Garmans,</hi> a poor man, yet much talkt of, who came now and then to her houſe.</p>
            <p>At this mans houſe I ſtayd about <hi>half a quarter of an hour,</hi> I had the rather a mind to ſee him, in that among others, I had heard Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> as well as others, particularly ſpeaking of him: This man about ſome two or three years after, with his Wife (as they ſaid) came to <hi>London,</hi> of whom I only heard, but ſaw them not; but having again, with my Wife, a <hi>Journey</hi> into the <hi>Weſt,</hi> we overtook, and left behind on foot, ſome half a dozen of <hi>men</hi> and <hi>Women</hi> on the <hi>Road;</hi> the next day, or the ſame day at even, we having ſtayed by the way, we overtook them again, about <hi>Marlborough,</hi> when, of the man that was with us, they enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my name, which when they knew, they ſtayed and ſpoke to me, going over a <hi>Bridge;</hi> I willingly went <hi>ſoftly</hi> to have ſome ſpeech with <hi>them,</hi> they telling me in <hi>effect</hi> they were, yea, <hi>that they</hi> were <hi>Jews,</hi> and that the time of their <hi>gathering together,</hi> out of all <hi>Lands,</hi> eſpecially <hi>this,</hi> was <hi>come,</hi> and that they ſhould <hi>away</hi> for <hi>Hieruſalem;</hi> yea, that they muſt be <hi>circumciſed,</hi> and ſo forth: To all which I <hi>replyed,</hi> that in a ſence I approved of all this, but not in their <hi>ſence,</hi> or as they <hi>applied</hi> it; but ſaid, <hi>that he is a</hi> Jew, <hi>and of the ſeed of Abraham that believs, whoſe praiſe is not of men, but of God:</hi> yea, the very ſame too, ſaid I, <hi>are the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion,</hi> which <hi>worſhip God</hi> in <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and ſo have the <hi>true Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion,</hi> which is <hi>yet</hi> that <hi>made without hands.</hi> Laſtly, <hi>the place</hi> of <hi>theſe</hi> I <hi>judged</hi> to be <hi>no other</hi> then <hi>Hieruſalem;</hi> but that I mean <hi>come down from Heaven,</hi> into which <hi>no unclean thing ſhall be</hi> admitted: as they <hi>liked</hi> not mine, ſo I <hi>diſowned</hi> their ſenſe of theſe things, as I am ſure I had the greater cauſe, after about half a miles riding, I left them, I going another way; about a twelve-moneth after, I came to <hi>London,</hi> and as I was going to dinner in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> about eleven of the Clock, or a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:118367:26"/>there met me a Merchant, that formerly I had knowledge of, and ſome acquaintance with, told me, that there were ſome at his <hi>houſe</hi> had a great deſire to ſpeak <hi>with me;</hi> I left my <hi>dinner,</hi> and went with him to a <hi>fair</hi> and <hi>great houſe,</hi> where I had never been before, he had me into an upper <hi>Room,</hi> where when I came, I <hi>heard</hi> a very <hi>great noyſe,</hi> of one ſpeaking I knew <hi>not what,</hi> with <hi>exceeding great fervency;</hi> I would have <hi>ſtayed,</hi> and <hi>heard further there,</hi> but he urged me to go where <hi>it was</hi> into the <hi>next Room,</hi> where I ſaw at the <hi>Table,</hi> the forenamed <hi>Garman wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> having before him an <hi>Hebrew Bible:</hi> there was ſome <hi>two or three</hi> men, beſides this <hi>Gentleman,</hi> whoſe houſe <hi>then it was,</hi> and my ſelf: in the <hi>Room</hi> was a <hi>Bed,</hi> and <hi>one ſitting</hi> up <hi>in it,</hi> ſpeaking as I ſaid <hi>before,</hi> and claping <hi>his hands</hi> with <hi>exceeding ſeeming height of confidence;</hi> but the words he ſpake I did not <hi>underſtand,</hi> only they <hi>ſeemed</hi> to me, <hi>to be a mixture of Latine, and ſome</hi> other <hi>tongues,</hi> (they ſaid <hi>Hebrew</hi>) and <hi>all other Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages</hi>) I confeſs, I remembred he mentioned <hi>oft Melchiſe deck,</hi> the <hi>High Prieſt,</hi> or <hi>Prieſt-hood,</hi> the <hi>name Judah,</hi> and <hi>Jeſus,</hi> with ſuch zeal, that the <hi>fire ſeemed to me, even to ſparkle out of his eyes:</hi> he did beſides, I remember, <hi>curſe with great bitterneſs the Prieſt-hood, as he ſaid, that was not after the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Melchiſedeck:</hi> by his ſide there lodg'd a Woman, which I confeſs I did ſuſpect was the Woman I had ſeen before at <hi>Wells,</hi> and after that upon the Road; but not underſtanding, and indeed, not <hi>approving</hi> of, yet <hi>wondring</hi> I confeſs, at the <hi>buſineſs,</hi> after leſs then a quarter of an hour, I <hi>departed,</hi> and have never ſeen them ſince.</p>
            <p>Now the truth is, as I have had opportunity, I have related the matter, as I here have done, to ſuch as I thought good, and in particular, did ſo now in my laſt journey, to one at <hi>Briſtol,</hi> from whom peradventure Mr. <hi>Wood</hi> hath had this Relation, or elſe I know not whence it ſhould ariſe; and peradventure, this man would I ſhould have gone and made ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of theſe people, as the manner of ſome is, to be very ſevere in complaining againſt, ſometimes, but the ſeeming evils of others, but in mean time, very ſparing of their own abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble luſts, the Seed and Poſterity of <hi>Saul,</hi> who kill and make an end, with great zeal forſooth, the leſſer Cattel of the Herds and Flock of <hi>Amaleck;</hi> but in mean time, ſave alive the fat and ſtrong.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:118367:26"/>
            <p> The Scriptures we all know declare, how that our <hi>Saviour</hi> was <hi>himſelf,</hi> not only in the <hi>Company,</hi> but left <hi>alone</hi> in the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> of an <hi>Adulterous Woman,</hi> whom the <hi>unſeen Adulterers</hi> had brought there before him to <hi>accuſe;</hi> ſo that certainly there is no cauſe of <hi>blame</hi> for my being (as I was) and coming as I did to this place; wherefore they have the <hi>greater ſin,</hi> who have made it firſt <hi>evil</hi> and <hi>wicked</hi> in their own <hi>hearts,</hi> out of which as the <hi>root of all filth,</hi> they have <hi>caſt it again forth,</hi> if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for <hi>the ſtaining the innocency and truth of God in me:</hi> ſo that I confeſs, I do not reject the ſtory <hi>as I have given it, and as it is, as the ſpirit</hi> and <hi>end</hi> for which it is produc'd.</p>
            <p>The third is, Mrs <hi>Ceenee's</hi> Lodging ſometimes at my houſe.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Wood,</hi> by this minds me of the <hi>rule</hi> which they ſay <hi>was Matchiavels,</hi> if a man be never ſo <hi>innocent,</hi> yet the way effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to <hi>ruine him,</hi> is <hi>audacter calumniare &amp; aliquid haerebit, lade</hi> him with <hi>reproach,</hi> and <hi>ſome,</hi> if not <hi>all,</hi> will be <hi>beleev'd</hi> of <hi>moſt:</hi> verily, I have been ſo dealt with to <hi>ſome purpoſe,</hi> by this and ſome other my friends at <hi>Windſor:</hi> the <hi>Scriptures</hi> ſpeaking of theſe <hi>latter times,</hi> ſays among others, there are theſe two <hi>Characters</hi> of the <hi>evil men</hi> found in <hi>them,</hi> that as they are ſuch that <hi>have eyes full of adultery,</hi> or the <hi>adultereſs;</hi> ſo they have an <hi>heart exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with covetous practiſes.</hi> Mr. <hi>Wood</hi> ſhall <hi>find</hi> where the <hi>lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is</hi> in the <hi>heart</hi> (ſure it will be found in his) which is <hi>Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> as to <hi>God;</hi> for it is <hi>covetouſneſs (forſooth no ſin in theſe times)</hi> which yet, ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> is <hi>Idolatry</hi> and the <hi>very ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix</hi> and <hi>root of all ſin; there</hi> I ſay without all <hi>peradventure</hi> is <hi>the</hi> other, if not in the <hi>body,</hi> yet in <hi>the eye:</hi> this ſure at leaſt was in <hi>the eye of Mr. Wood,</hi> he would <hi>elſe not have reproacht me with</hi> the entertainment of this Woman; for aſſuredly, ſhe was in my <hi>account,</hi> yea doubtleſs in <hi>the account</hi> of thoſe made her the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron</hi> of the <hi>Savoy,</hi> a <hi>Woman ſober,</hi> and of good <hi>report;</hi> yea, I <hi>ſuppoſe,</hi> with the <hi>Governour</hi> and <hi>others here,</hi> who had ſpeech and acquaintance with her, as well as I, ſhe having two Children in <hi>theſe parts,</hi> and one of them at <hi>Eaton-School:</hi> as touching her entertainment at <hi>my houſe,</hi> I am <hi>confident,</hi> it was <hi>deſign'd,</hi> if by any means they might <hi>by her enſnare me,</hi> a practice <hi>uſed by the Heathen</hi> of old, againſt the <hi>holy men</hi> and <hi>Martyrs of God,</hi> to <hi>find</hi> occaſion againſt them <hi>to take away their lives;</hi> ſhe came I confeſs in an <hi>affright</hi> to my dwelling in the <hi>Caſtle,</hi> ſhe being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed of the <hi>Souldiers,</hi> to return (as ſhe ſaid) to her Lodging, I
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118367:27"/>adviſed her, that being <hi>innocent,</hi> ſhe had no cauſe to <hi>fear</hi> to go before the <hi>Governour,</hi> before whom they told her, ſhe muſt <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear;</hi> ſhe did accordingly, when being as ſhe ſaid, <hi>threatned to be put</hi> into the cuſtody of the <hi>Marſhal,</hi> ſhe deſired ſhe might have leave to go to her wonted <hi>Lodging,</hi> which was at one <hi>Harriſes</hi> in the <hi>Caſtle,</hi> by no means this might be, <hi>but ſaith the Governor, you may ſee whether you may not ſtay at Mr. Bacons;</hi> wherefore at his moving, ſhe came to deſire me to go to him, when I came, the <hi>Governors</hi> firſt demand of me <hi>was, whether I would paſſe my word for Mrs. Ceenee,</hi> I told him no, nor ye for any one <hi>elſe:</hi> the next was, whether to prevent her going to the <hi>Marſhal,</hi> ſhe ſhould abide at my <hi>houſe,</hi> I ſaid, I thought rather then that ſhe ſhould be in <hi>distreſs,</hi> my Wife would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide ſome Lodgings for her, which ſhe did, and I conſented to, in the <hi>ſimplicity</hi> and <hi>uprightneſs of our hearts;</hi> it was a frequent <hi>charge,</hi> the <hi>Phariſees</hi> brought againſt <hi>Jeſus,</hi> that he was a friend of <hi>Publicans</hi> and <hi>Harlots, God</hi> hath had <hi>mercy on me in this,</hi> to <hi>drink of the ſame Cup</hi> from <hi>men</hi> of <hi>like ſpirit</hi> with <hi>them;</hi> but <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce</hi> and be <hi>exceeding glad,</hi> for <hi>this hath been the lot of the juſt from the beginning of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt of Mr. <hi>Woods</hi> good ſpeeches of <hi>me,</hi> is, that he and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers cannot tell, when if at any time they come to hear me, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I will ſpeak either from, or of God, or the Devil: ſay we <hi>not well,</hi> ſaid the <hi>Jews</hi> to our <hi>Saviour,</hi> thou art a <hi>Samaritan,</hi> and haſt a <hi>Devil;</hi> yet we know <hi>(that beleeve)</hi> of what <hi>ſpirit</hi> our <hi>Saviour was,</hi> how by the finger of <hi>God</hi> he caſt out <hi>Devils,</hi> yet they <hi>ſaid,</hi> it was by <hi>Beelzebub;</hi> wherefore ſaid <hi>he</hi> (and I ſay the like to Mr. <hi>Wood</hi>) all <hi>ſins and blaſphemies ſhall be forgiven unto men, ſave that againſt the holy Spirit;</hi> but I will conclude with only theſe two ſayings, They that are <hi>of God, hear,</hi> and can hear alone <hi>his word,</hi> and he that <hi>knoweth God,</hi> and is <hi>born of him, heareth us,</hi> and he that is <hi>not of God,</hi> heareth <hi>not us:</hi> in <hi>this,</hi> or <hi>by this,</hi> we <hi>diſcern betwixt the ſpirit of God,</hi> and the <hi>ſpirit of this World,</hi> the <hi>ſpirit of truth,</hi> and the <hi>ſpirit of error.</hi> Mr. <hi>Wood,</hi> and others of the ſame mind with him, profeſſeth in this charge, that he hath no diſcerning of the one of theſe from the other, and ſo muſt needs be a peece of that man of ſin, of which the Scripture ſaith ſhould come, and even now is in the world.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
